<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Motives of conversion to the Catholick faith, as it is professed in the reformed Church of England by Neal Carolan ...</title>
            <author>Carolan, Neal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15923</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12544926</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12544926</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63025</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63025)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 308:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Motives of conversion to the Catholick faith, as it is professed in the reformed Church of England by Neal Carolan ...</title>
                  <author>Carolan, Neal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Jos. Ray for William Norman ... and Eliphal Dobson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 67.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63025:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOTIVES OF CONVERSION TO THE CATHOLICK FAITH, As it is PROFESSED IN THE REFORMED CHURCH OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Neal Carolan,</hi> formerly Parish-Prieſt of <hi>Slane</hi> and <hi>Stacallan, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Meath.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <p>Aug. 8. 1688.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Rad. Rule, R. R. in Chriſto Patri, ac Domino Domino Franciſco Archiep. Dublin. à ſacr. domeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Joſ: Ray,</hi> for <hi>William Norman</hi> in <hi>Dames-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Eliphal Dobſon</hi> at the <hi>Stationers Arms</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63025:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63025:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>IT is juſt and reaſonable that every man that deſerts the Communion of a Church in which he hath been educated, and embraceth a Communion diſtinct from it, ſhould render ſome accompt to the world of the reaſons of his change, that ſo he might avoid the imputation of levity and raſhneſs. This hath been done by many of the Proteſtants that have embraced the Roman Faith; namely, by <hi>Dr. Vane, Mr. Creſſy, Mr. Manby,</hi> and others, and by many Romaniſts, that have embraced the Reformed Religion, by the Learned Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> and ſeveral others, and being my ſelf reſolved to forſake the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to embrace that of the Reformed Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which I think more agreeable to the Word of God, and to the Primitive Antiquity, I look on my ſelf to be under the ſame obligations of ſatisfying others, in the Motives of my change.</p>
            <p>As it was my great happineſs to be Baptized into the Chriſtian Faith, ſo it was my misfortune to be educated in that which is far diſtant from it (I mean the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Faith) as it now ſtands ſince the determinations of the Council of <hi>Trent:</hi> and I hope the Gentlemen of that Religion will not take it ill that I call it an infelicity, ſince I can entertain no other apprehenſions of it, whilſt I lie under the convictious that are at preſent upon my Spirit.</p>
            <p>In the Communion of this Church I was admitted into the ſeven Holy Orders of the Church in a weeks time, by <hi>Anthony Geoghegan,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Meath</hi> in the Year <hi>1662,</hi> and in the month of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in the ſame Year I was ſent to <hi>Paris,</hi> where I was inſtructed in Phyloſophy in the College of <hi>Graſſini,</hi> and took the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Maſter in Arts, in the Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> aforeſaid, and after Writing my Speculative Divinity in the College of <hi>Navar</hi> in the ſaid Univerſity, under <hi>Dr. Vinot, Dr. Sauſſoy,</hi> and <hi>Dr. Ligny,</hi> I finiſhed my courſe, and took up a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of returning to my Native Country, where I landed about <hi>June 1667,</hi> and afterwards continued about ſome two years teaching a private School in the Borders of <hi>Meath,</hi> till in the year <hi>1669,</hi> I was inſtituted into the Pariſh of <hi>Slane,</hi> and <hi>Stacallan,</hi> by <hi>Oliver Deſſe,</hi> then Vicar General of the Dioreſs of <hi>Meath,</hi> where I continued as Pariſh Prieſt for four intire years, to the no ſmall content and ſatisfaction of my Pariſhioners: from them in the year <hi>1675,</hi> I was removed to the Pariſhes of <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtown,</hi> and <hi>Brownſtown,</hi> and in the year <hi>79.</hi> commanded back again to my firſt charge in <hi>Slan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During this time, I had the opportunity of reading two Bookes that were moſt eſpecially recommended to the Clergy of the Province of <hi>U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter,</hi> by the late Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate <hi>Oliver Plunket,</hi> viz. <hi>Archdokins Theologia Tripartita,</hi> and the <hi>Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Goſpel.</hi> The former of theſe he diſtributed amongſt us, at a certain price, when the firſt impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion of it came forth, and the latter we were
<pb facs="tcp:63025:3"/>required to purchaſe, as being very proper to confute Proteſtants out of their own Bibles. I was no leſs forward in procuring the Books, then induſtrious in reading them, and for a long time I thought them unanſwerable, till at length diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing with ſome of the Reverend Proteſtant Clergy of <hi>Meath,</hi> I found by them that the <hi>Touchſtone,</hi> was only an old Book new vampt up with a new Title, and ſome few Chapters added, and that it had been long ago publiſhed, under the Title of the <hi>Gag</hi> for the new <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and learnedly been anſwered by the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhop <hi>Mountague.</hi> Whereupon I procured the anſwer to it, and upon peruſal found that the Author of the Old <hi>Gag</hi> ro New <hi>Touchſtone</hi> (call it which you pleaſe) had in many things baſely miſrepreſented the Doctrine of the Proteſtants, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding it in ſuch crude, and indifinite terms as no ſober Proteſtant doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it for their ſenſe: as in his <hi>2d,</hi> Propoſition he affirms, <hi>that Proteſtants ſay that in matters of Faith, We muſt not relye upon the judgment of the Church, and of her Paſtors, but only on the written word.</hi> In the <hi>3d, that the Scriptures are eaſily to be underſtood.</hi> In the 4th, <hi>that Apoſtolical Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and ancient cuſtoms of the Church (not found in the written word) are not to to be received, nor oblige.</hi> In the <hi>5th, that a man by his own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or private Spirit, may rightly judge and interpret Scripture.</hi> In the <hi>7th, that the Church can erre.</hi> In the <hi>32, that the Saints may not pray for us,</hi> and ſo in others. None of which Propoſitions are owned by Proteſtants, as their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines without many previous diſtinctions and limitations. I found alſo that in other things he had hudled together many Propoſitions as the general ſenſe of Proteſtants, which (if he had conſulted their learned Writings) he would have found to be no more then School Points, and Problematical Queſtions; nay, which are ſtill diſputed as ſuch by the beſt learned men in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Such are for Example, <hi>The Doctrines of Freewill,</hi> in the <hi>19th</hi> Propoſition, <hi>The Impoſſibility of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commandements,</hi> in the <hi>20th</hi> Propoſition, <hi>The Inamiſſibility of Faith,</hi> in the <hi>23th, The Doctrine of Election, and Reprobation,</hi> in the <hi>24th, The Doctrine of Aſſurance of Salvation.</hi> in the <hi>25th</hi> and <hi>The Doctrine of every m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n having his Guardian Angel,</hi> in the <hi>26th,</hi> moſt of which Points are matter of Controverſie between Remonſtrants, and Contra-remonſtrants amongſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, And between the Janſeniſts and Jeſuits in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This unfair proceeding, charging the Proteſtants with Doctrines, which they either totally deny, or do not acknowledge without previous diſtinctions, bred a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in me to the Book, and conſequently put me upon an inquiry into thoſe Doctrines of the Proteſtants which the Author of it had ſo fouly miſrepreſented, and the more I read in their Writings the better I was reconciled to their Opinions, and the worſe I liked thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſome of whoſe Errors I ſhall brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch, as the Motives of my Converſion, and occaſion of my deſerting her Communion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63025:3"/>
            <head>Motives of Converſion to the Catholick Faith, as it is profeſſed in the Reformed Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs of the Church of</hi> Rome.</head>
               <p>THE firſt Motive thereof is her great Uncharitableneſs, not only to Proteſtants, but alſo to all other Societies of Chriſtians this day in the World except themſelves; and that in two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In confining the Catholick Church to themſelves.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In excluding all others from hope of Salvation that are not in their own Communion.</p>
               <p>It will be unneceſſary to prove that theſe are the Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince there is no Controvertiſt that doth not affirm them, and they are expreſly defined in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> in her <hi>Anathema</hi> to every Article. And Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV. affirms in his Bull, <hi>That this is the Catholick Faith, out of which no one can be ſaved.</hi> All the Clergy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> whether Secular or Regular, are taught to ſay ſo; the Prieſts and Friers affirm it in their Sermons now to the People more than ever: And it is one of the moſt popular Arguments and common Topicks of Converſion that they all uſe to the Proteſtants, to reconcile them to the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> That they are all Hereticks; That they are out of the Church; That there is no hopes of Salvation for them whileſt they are ſo.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> Confining of the Catholick Church to themſelves, is a Propoſition ſo hugely unreaſonable that I could hardly bring my ſelf to the belief of it. It ſeemed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63025:4"/>to me a very unreaſonable thing, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is but a Member of the Catholick Church (and that none of the foundeſt) ſhould arrogate to it ſelf the Name and Priviledges of the whole Catholick<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Quia à dicto ſecundùm quid, ad dictum ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter non valet conſequentia; Nec ſemper denominatio totius ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur partes ſeperatim ſumptas.</hi> And I could find no Text of Scripture for the juſtification of it, nor any ſound Reaſon to prove it, nor any promiſe of our Saviour on which to ground it; and I concluded with my ſelf, that the affirming it might prove a dangerous prejudice to the perpetuity of the Church, and contradict our Saviours promiſe concerning the Gates of Hell not being able to prevail againſt it, becauſe it was not only poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as other Churches, might err, but there are expreſs Cautions given her in that particular by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom 11.18, 20. <hi>Thou beareſt not the root, but the root thee: Be not high minded but fear, and if God ſpareth not the natural branches, take heed leaſt he alſo ſpare not thee.</hi> In the Writings of the Primitive Fathers it appears, that they never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be any thing elſe but a particular Church. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in the Title of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſtiles it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> reckons the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in the ſame rank with the Churches of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Alexandria:</hi> So that if they were parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, or topical Churches, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be ſo too. The ſame thing doth Pope
<note n="*" place="margin">Apud Binium in Concil. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſino.</note> 
                  <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> where he reckons up the Churches of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> as Members of the Catholick Church. <hi>Aſſeret ſe</hi> (Neſtorius) <hi>fidem tenere, quam ſecundum Apoſtolicam doctrinam Romana, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrina, &amp; Catholica univerſalis Eccleſia tenet.</hi> Nay it appears by the Epiſtle of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> III. to <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 200.</note> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that in the 12th Century the Pope himſelf did not believe it. <hi>Dicitur autem univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Eccleſia, quae de univerſis conſtet Eccleſiis, quae Graeco Verbo Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica nominatur:</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Eccleſia Romana ſic non eſt univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Eccleſia, ſed univerſalis Eccleſiae pars.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63025:4"/>
               <p>Beſides this, I find this very Propoſition condemned in the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts,</hi> and looked upon by the Fathers as the grand Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Principle of their Schiſm and Diviſion; for they, as appears by the Writings of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Optatus,</hi> did affirm that Chriſt had no Church on Earth, but in the parts of <hi>Donatus:</hi> that the Church was periſhed in all parts of the World except their own Aſſemblies, and that Salvation no where could be had but in their Communion; they eſteemed the reſt of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to be no better than Pagans: they broke their Chalices, ſcraped their Altars, and waſhed their Veſtments, and the Walls of their Churches, pretending that all was polluted by their touch of them. How much of this Spirit doth reign in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Donatiſts is eaſily obſerved by any man that will take the pains to compare their Writings and Practiſes with thoſe of their Anceſtors, the antient Donatiſts in <hi>Africk.</hi> And indeed it is high time for every man to leave the ſociety of that Perſon that thinks himſelf alone to have reaſon, and all the reſt of mankind to be mad and out of their wits.</p>
               <p>Nor is this Propoſition only unreaſonable, but is alſo very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, in as much as it condemns not only Proteſtant Churches, but all the Chriſtians in the Eaſtern parts of the World that are not of the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith; the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> the <hi>Jacobites</hi> and <hi>Neſtorians,</hi> the <hi>Maronites</hi> and <hi>Abiſſines,</hi> and <hi>Coph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and for ever excludes them from hopes of Salvation; which is in effect to unchurch the greateſt part of Chriſtians, and condemn them to everlaſting burnings; who are more in number, and more extend in Territories then the Profeſſors of the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Faith can pretend to be; notwithſtanding all their brags of Univerſality. It may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſaid, that the Eaſtern Chriſtians and Proteſtants are Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks: but I think it much eaſier to ſay ſo than make it good; and if they were, yet the charity of the modern <hi>Bomaniſts</hi> is much more ſtreightned than that of St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> was,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Baptiſ. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Don. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> who durſt not deny a poſſibility of Salvation, even to He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks themſelves. For when the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that Hereſio is an Harlot, that if Baptiſm of Hereticks be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63025:5"/>good, then Sons are born to God of Hereſie; and ſo of an Harlot. His Anſwer was, that the Conventicles of Hereticks do bear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto God; not in that wherein they are divided, but in that wherein they ſtill remain join'd with the True &amp; Catholick Church; not in that they are Hereticks, but as much as they profeſs and practiſe that which other Chriſtians do. Nay, according to the Opinion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors they have no reaſon (if they ſtand to their own Principles) to judg ſo ſeverely of Hereticks; for they grant that the honour of Martyrdom is only peculiar to the Members of the Catholick Church; and they cannot deny but it is poſſible for an Heritick to ſuffer for the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and lay down his life in the defence of the Faith of Chriſt: From whence it muſt inevitably follow, according to their own confeſſions, that either Hereticks may be ſaved, or elſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom is not proper to the Church and Members of it.</p>
               <p>Nor are the Romaniſts only unreaſonable, and uncharitable, in confining the Catholick Church to themſelves, but they are ſo in excluding alſo other Chriſtians from the hopes of Salvation that are not of their own Communion. This will appear from two Conſiderations. Firſt, they are more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable to them then they are to Heathens that never heard of Jeſus Chriſt: for
<note n="*" place="margin">Lud. Vives in Aug. de Civitat Dei. l. 18. c. 47. Andr. id. l. 3. At alii apud Caſail. de quadripli juſtit. l. 1. c. 12 &amp; Collium de anim. pag. l. 1. c. 24. &amp; l. 5. c. 7, 8, 22.</note> many of their own Writers do grant a poſſibility of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Pagans, if they live good moral lives, and yet the Proteſtants, thô they believe in Chriſt, and profeſs all the Articles of the Apoſtles Creed, and lead their lives ſuitable to the Goſpel, muſt be damned to Hell; only becauſe they cannot believe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be their Miſtreſs, nor call the Pope their Maſter on Earth.</p>
               <p>It ſeems that Infidelity is a leſſer crime then Non-Communion with <hi>Rome;</hi> that there is more hopes of <hi>Pagans,</hi> then of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> to be ſaved, and that it is more pardonable not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt Jeſus then to deny the authority of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> In that many of them make ſo few things to be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be believed in order to eternal ſalvation, that upon their own Principles they cannot exclude the Proteſtants from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63025:5"/>hopes of it; and for thoſe that inlarge the Articles of Belief a little farther, they cannot deny Salvation to the Proteſtants, if they believe all that they require as neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Some men make the Belief of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſubmiſſion to his Laws, ſufficient to bring a man to Heaven; and if ſo, it is very uncharitable to exclude Proteſtants from it, that believe ſo much, as well as themſelves. Others add the knowledge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of thoſe things that are contained in the Lords Prayer, and the Ten Commandments, and Doctrin of the Sacraments. Now take the explicite <hi>credenda,</hi> in which of theſe Notions you will, it is hugely uncharitable, to exclude the Proteſtants out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, when they believe Jeſus Chriſt to be the Son of God, and ſubmit to his Laws, and live according to his Religion; when they believe all that is contained in the Creed, the Lords Prayer, and the Decalogue, and aſſent to the Doctrin of thoſe Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are generally neceſſary for ſalvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Infallibility of the Pope.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE ſecond Motive is, The Doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church concerning the Infallibility of the Pope; alſo concerning an Infallible Church and General Council, and concerning the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Judg or Guide in Controverſies about Religion, which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> talk ſo much of, and pretend to have.</p>
               <p>No man certainly that fully conſiders the various models of an Infallible Guide which the ſeveral parties of Papiſts do deſcribe and defend in oppoſition to one another, will wonder that I have given this Chapter a manifold Title. The great uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and confuſion of Opinions which I found in the Romiſh Communion about this affair was not the leaſt cauſe of my being diſcontented with that Religion: It ſtartled me exceedingly at the beginning of my inquiry, to find the main Pillar of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Doctrin (that is the Infallible Director above mentioned)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63025:6"/>was only a name without any reality, for there is little or nothing ſet up by one party under this name or title which is not ſtrongly confuted by another of the Roman Catholicks; yet they all join to run down the Proteſtants for having a Religion built upon no ſecure foundation; for all Religion is ſo inſecurely built (if we believe the Romaniſts) which is not bottomed upon the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of ſome viſible Infallible director; whether that be the unerring guidance or direction of the Pope, as ſome think, or of a Pope and General Council together, as others do judg; or of a Council without the Pope, and acting under an aſſumed Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, as a third ſort imagine. Now it is true indeed, that our Faith, ought to rely upon an Infallible Foundation, and the written Word of God is the thing, and the vain pretence of a viſible unerring Judge, or Guide; is nothing but mere conceit, as I ſhall hereafter plainly ſhew.</p>
               <p>Therefore I look upon my ſelf at preſent as obliged to acquaint the Reader, how much I found my ſelf miſtaken concerning this Infallible Guide, which heretofore I very much relied upon. When I entered into an enquiry, and would very gladly have conſulted him, and take his advice, immediately I found my ſelf loſt in an endleſs wilderneſs of Diſputes, diſſentions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent Opinions concerning him: For the writers of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church are divided into ſeveral Sects about this affair, and what one party of them ſets up, another party pulls down and rejects.</p>
               <p>Moſt Divines that have dependance on the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and likewiſe many others, maintain that the Pope is Infallible in his own Perſon; and that he needs not the concurrence of general Councils, but can make Infallible Decrees concerning Faith and Manners, by himſelf alone: yet they are not well agreed about this neither.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albertus Pighius</hi> (as it is reported by <hi>Cardinal Bell. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2, <hi>de Rom. Pont.</hi>) was of opinion, that the Pope could not become a Heretick, neither in his private capacity, nor when he acted publickly by his Pontifical Authority. Now the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, thô a great Aſſertor of Papal Priviledges, yer condemns
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63025:6"/>this Opinion of <hi>Pighius</hi> for an extravagance. Thus</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The third Opinion <hi>(for he had cited two before)</hi> is in the other extream,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertia ſententia eſt in altero ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremo Pontificem non poſſe ullo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do eſſe Haereticum, nec docere pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licè Haereſin, etiamſi rem aliquam ſolus definiat. Ita Albertus Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hius, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Hierarch. Eccl.</hi>
                     </note> that the Pope in no way can become an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, nor publickly teach Hereſie, although he defines ſome things by himſelf alone.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs not only this Cardinal, but alſo <hi>Cajetan,</hi> and <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> moſt of the order of the Jeſuites, and in ſhort, all the Divines of the <hi>Italian</hi> Faction, do ſtifly maintain the perſonal Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Pope: In ſome ſenſe indeed more moderatly, and in ſome ſenſe more extravagantly, then <hi>Pighius;</hi> for they are more moderate in acknowledging that the Pope in his private capacity may become a Heretick, and much worſe. Yet they conſtantly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that in his publick capacity, and when he makes uſe of his Pontifical Authority, then he cannot poſſibly be in the wrong, nor teach any falſe Doctrin: And this Poſition they endeavor to make good, by the beſt Arguments they can get: Every little ſhadow of proof, that occurrs either in the holy Scripture, or in the Fathers, is ſetched out in order to confirm this pretended unerring priviledg of the <hi>Roman</hi> Prelate. Amongſt other things the Example of the Jewiſh high Prieſt is thought to have ſome weight in it, thô ſome of thoſe were Idolaters; and one, that is <hi>Caiphas,</hi> by the ſame ſentence condemned Chriſt for a Deceiver, and the whole Chriſtian Religion for an Impoſture. Now the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctors being urged with this mighty Scandal, and ſhame to Pontifical Infallibility, do (ſome of them) give this anſwer; that <hi>Caiphas</hi> miſtook the matter of Fact, but not the matter of Faith. See <hi>Bell. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Concil. de Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate Rom. Pont.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the wiſe Author of the <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented,</hi> pag. 46. brings this Example of <hi>Caiphas</hi> upon the ſtage, not conſidering that it is ſo far from being any way advantagious to the pretence of the <hi>Roman Pontiff,</hi> that it even diſgraces the very name of High Prieſt. This Author, <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>pag</hi> 46. ſpeaking of the Grace
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63025:7"/>and Aſſiſtance which God in ſome inſtances gave to Perſons emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in Office; and particularly to <hi>Capiphas,</hi> when he judged it neceſſary that Chriſt ſhould be put to death for the conſervation of the Nations: he ſays, <q rend="margQuotes">With like helping Grace, he doubts not but God generally aſſiſts the Paſtors of the New Law, and more eſpecially the High Prieſt (that is the Pope) for the good of the whole Flock. And therefore thô he were as wicked as <hi>Caiphas,</hi> yet he is ready to render him all reſpect due to his Function, and to obey him in every thing concerning the exerciſe of his Charge, not for any conſideration of his Perſon, but meerly for the Office he bears.</q> Let the Reader obſerve the words of this Author; what a notable guide the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is according to this mans deſcription of him; His extraordinary endowments in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducting Souls to Heaven is compared unto the Grace which <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> had when he falſly and unjuſtly condemned our Saviour for a Deceiver; and conſequently the whole Chriſtian Religion for a deceit. Nothing certainly can be more ſtrange, unleſs it be what Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſays concerning Papal Infallibilty, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Rom. Pont. c.</hi> 5. he maintains that the Pope hath a priviledge of being free from error, in making any publick Decree what ever relating to Faith or Practiſe; and he carrys the Aſſertion ſo high as to ſay, that <q rend="margQuotes">If the Pope ſhould err by command ing Vices,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Si Papa erraret praecipiendo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, vel prohibendo virtutes, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neretur Ecclaeſia credere vitia eſſe bona, &amp; virtutes malas, niſi vellet contra conſcientiam peccare. Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Rom. Pont. Cap.</hi> 5.</note> and forbidding Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, the Church would be bound to believe, that Vices were good, and Vertues evil; unleſs it would ſin againſt Conſcience.</q> Wonderful Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p>Certainly no man of any reaſon or honeſty but will abhor ſuch a Poſition; and accordingly <hi>Bellarmines</hi> heart ſmote him in his old age for having delivered ſuch a thing: And therefore in his Recognition upon this paſſage he minced the matter, and partly recalled this wild ſaying, perhaps when he was near death, and had no hopes to obtain the Papacy for himſelf; then he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63025:7"/>to ſpeak more ſoberly concerning the Power and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Pope.</p>
               <p>But above all men commend me to <hi>Coſterus</hi> the Jeſuite, for a wonderful Teacher of Papal Infallibility. He ſays, <q rend="margQuotes">It may come to paſs, as we confeſs, that the Succeſſor of St.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fatemur fieri poſſe, ut</hi> Petri <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor Idola colat, apud ſe forte de Fide non recte ſentiens; ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oque Artibus Diabolicis operam navet. Sed conſtanter negamus Vicarios Chriſti, Petrique Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſores. Romanos Pontifices, vel Haereſin alios docere poſſe, vel Errorem proponere. Coſt. Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter</hi> may worſhip Idols, privately perhaps, having a wrong Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concerning the Faith; and may conſequently be a Studier of Diabolical Arts. But this we conſtantly deny, that the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> Vicars of Chriſt, and Succeſſors of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> can teach Hereſie to others, or propoſe an Error.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Whether <hi>Coſterus,</hi> when he delivered this, had an eye to thoſe Popes, who have been accuſed of being Magicians, and invoking Devils, I cannot determin. But I appeal to all perſons endu'd with Reaſon, and let them judge whether I had not juſt cauſe to grow very much diſſatisfied with that Communion, whoſe Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers do firſt make it neceſſary for all Chriſtians to bottom and ground their Faith and Religion upon the credit of an Infallible Guide, and then they give the moſt lewd deſcription of him that ever was heard. One that may be an Idolater, a Wizard and an Infidel, an Heretick in his private capacity, one that is notwithſtanding to be obeyed, if he command Vices, and forbid Vertues; and if he command ſo, all Chriſtians are bound to believe Vices to be good, and Vertues evil: one that is an Infallible Guide, ſuch as <hi>Caiphas</hi> was: one that has as much ſecurity and certainty of being in the right as <hi>Caiphas</hi> had. Whence it follows, that the Chriſtians, who rely on the Pope, have juſt as much certainty of being in the right, as the <hi>Jews</hi> in our Saviours time had of being ſo, by relying on their High Prieſt; yet they, notwithſtanding the infallible Conduct of <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi> cryed againſt Chriſt, <hi>crucifie him, crucifie him; and releaſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63025:8"/>unto us</hi> Barabbas. Doubtleſs theſe men, who deſcribe and prove the Popes Infallibility after ſuch a manner, as you have heard, are very blamable. Methinks they ſhould have more regard to the Honour of a Prince, than to have characterized him as they do. I know it was not done out of any ill will, but it is uſual for too officious Servants ſometimes to do their Maſters as much hurt, as if they were real Enemies.</p>
               <p>Thus the Reader will fully perceive how little ſatisfaction I found in the pretended unerring Guide, or Conductor, which the Italian Papiſts do propoſe. It is manifeſt there is very little comfort or ſecurity in the Conduct of ſuch a Guide. But being diſappointed in expecting infallible Guidance from any one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſuch as the Pope is, whom the Italian Paraſites advance; I proceeded to conſider another unerrable Guide, which the French Divines ſet up in oppoſition to the Italians, that is, a General Council. This indeed at firſt appeared unto me to have the faireſt pretenſion to be the Guide ſo much talked of. I ſuppoſe it well known, that in <hi>France</hi> the Perſonal Infallibility is generally rejected and decryed, as an untrue and groundleſs thing; and many large Diſcourſes have been written by the French Divines, in order to prove not only that the Pope may be deceived, but alſo that he has been very often actually ſo, even in matters of the greateſt importance. The Diſcourſes writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Gerſon</hi> above 250 years ago are abundantly known to all men of Reading.
<note place="margin">Tract. An liceat in cauſis Fidei à ſummo Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice appellare.</note> And in later times <hi>Launoius,</hi> a <hi>Sorbon</hi> Doctor, in many places of his Epiſtles, not only declares his own Senſe againſt the Perſonal Infallibility of the Pope, but likewiſe the Senſe or Judgment of the Gallican Church. He reproaches one <hi>Baro,</hi> his adverſary, for holding the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to be incapable of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and counts <hi>Baro</hi> to be a Traytor to the Gallican Church and Nation for it. I ſhall produce one paſſage out of <hi>Launoius</hi> to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Thus he inveighs againſt <hi>Baro,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Gallicanam graſſatur Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam, quae Romanum Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ſubmittit Concilio, &amp; ei non errandi in fide, &amp; moribus privilegium abjudicat ſed ſoli ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicat Eccleſia, &amp; Eccleſiam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guranti Concilio. Launoius Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolarum parte 5ta. Epiſtola ad Fortinum, pag.</hi> 43. <hi>vide etiam pag.</hi> 93.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">He perniciouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the Church of <hi>France,</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63025:8"/>which makes the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> inferiour to a Council, and decrees againſt his Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of not erring in Faith and Manners, and contrariwiſe adjudges it only to the Church and to a Council, the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative thereof.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here we have ſeen this learned <hi>Sorbon</hi> Doctor directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the Italian Divines concerning this affair, which is under debate. It is likewiſe very well known, that <hi>Richerius,</hi> another Doctor of <hi>Sorbon,</hi> and as good a Roman Catholick as the beſt of them, has written his Hiſtory of General Councils on ſet purpoſe therein to run down and demoliſh the Perſonal Infallibility, and other pretended Priviledges of the Pope. But above all <hi>Monſieur Maimbourg</hi> (a moſt inveterate Enemy to the Proteſtant Religion) has compoſed a Book deſignedly to confute the vain pretence of Papal Infallibility; and in the ſixth Chapter of that Book above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned he alledges all manner of Authorities, in order to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince mankind, that the Pope is not infallible; and he clearly makes out his Allegations i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 10 Chapters of the Book aforeſaid, concerning the Prerogatives of <hi>Rome</hi> and her Biſhop. That which is very pleaſant is, that <hi>Maimbourg</hi> finds ſeveral Popes, who thought their Predeceſſors fallible, and ſome, though but a few, who thought themſelves ſo too, Among theſe <hi>Adrian</hi> VI. like a modeſt and honeſt man, when he was actually Pope, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to own in general, and without exception, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> might fall into Error. <hi>Maimbourgs</hi> words are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Adrian</hi> VI. in his <hi>Commentaries upon the</hi> 4th <hi>of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,</hi> ſays poſitively, and in a moſt deciſive manner. That he is certain,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cortum eſt, quod Pontifex poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit errare etiam in iis, quae tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt fidem, Haereſin, per ſuam determinationem aut Decretalem aſſerendo. cap.</hi> 15. <hi>pag.</hi> 183.</note> the Pope may err even in matters belonging to Faith, teaching and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Hereſie by his Definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or by his Decretal.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it manifeſtly appears, that the French Catholicks are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63025:9"/>in this regard, oppoſite to the Italian Papiſts. Therefore <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> will not let this French Doctrine paſs, it being very preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the Intereſt of the papal Chair at <hi>Rome;</hi> but he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts it, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>de Romano Pontifice,</hi> and that very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely, ſaying, <hi>(videtur erronea, &amp; Haereſi proxima)</hi> it ſeems to be wholly erroneous, and next in the world to Hereſie. Here let the Reader conſider how thoſe Doctors of the Popiſh Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſagree and contradict each other about their pretended infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Judge or Guide in matters of Religion.</p>
               <p>The French Divines and Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> VI hold, that the Pope is not infallible, and they ſay, that the diffuſive Church and a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council is ſo. Then comes Cardinal <hi>Bellarm</hi> with others like him, and gives them the lye; and then they of the other ſide, not willing to dye in this debt, do the like to him and his aſſociates.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, that both parties had more manners than to tax one another with the lye in expreſs terms, that is true indeed, but yet they do the ſame in effect.</p>
               <p>Finding this great diſcord amongſt them, I ſet aſide the whole Italian Sect at once, and could have been content, if the French party had been able to advance a model of an infallible Guide with any concord amongſt themſelves, and without contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another.</p>
               <p>But alas they alſo are full of Diſputes and Diſſentions, and the beſt model they deviſe is liable to very great exceptions. As for Diſputes and Controverſy the matter is thus; Some hold, that a General Council is the only infallible Guide and Judge in things appertaining to Religion, but they allow the Pope many great priviledges in the Council. For example, a General Council (ſay one party) cannot be called, but by the Popes Authority, or by his Conſent. And the opinion of theſe men is to be found in <hi>Petrus de Marca</hi> the late famous Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Concordia Sacerdotii &amp; Imperii, cap.</hi> 5. <hi>parag.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Others affirm again, that the Civil Magiſtrate may call an extraordinary Council, which was the Judgment of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> publickly declared by the Command of King <hi>Charles</hi> VIII. as may be ſeen in the 4th <hi>Book of the Hiſtory of General
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63025:9"/>Councils</hi> ſet forth by <hi>Richerius</hi> above mentioned. <hi>C.</hi> 2. and the ſame was likewiſe the judgment of the late Famous Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris. Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>C.</hi> 17.4. <hi>de concordia Sacerdotii &amp; Imperii.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A third ſort hold it not to be abſolutely neceſſary that the Pope ſhould have any hand in conſtituting a General Council, or in preſiding in it, or in ratifying the Decrees of it. And this is the Opinion of <hi>Monſieur Maimbourg</hi> in his Book concerning the Prerogatives of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her Biſhop. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. <hi>Pag.</hi> 188, 189. The ſame Opinion is likewiſe maintained by <hi>Richerius, Hiſtoria Concil. General. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. For in two General Councils, that is the ſecond and fifth, the Pope neither preſided by himſelf, nor by his Delegates; and the ſame <hi>Richerius</hi> diſproves the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours and pretences found out by <hi>Baronius</hi> and <hi>Binius,</hi> in order to make the World believe that the Pope had ſome preſidency in the Councils above named. Hitherto we find nothing in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of this Infallible Guide, but uncertainty and confuſion, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Diſputes, and endleſs Quarrels. This I conſidered, and was exceedingly troubled, to find my ſelf ſo mightily deceived in my expectation.</p>
               <p>But let us proceed farther, and ſee whether any thing in the World be conſiſtent, and credible in this French Doctrin: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their model of an Infallible Guide, I am content to ſet aſide the manifold Diſputes, concerning the nature and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of a Council, on condition I may find them well agreed for the reſt. Notwithſtanding, if they were perfectly agreed, and as harmonious as Muſick, yet there lies very many excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt their Opinion: for if a General Council be the only thing incapable of Error, then it follows inevitably, that there has been no viſible Infallible Guide upon earth for theſe 120 years laſt paſt. For it is ſo long ſince any thing pretending to be a General Council was in being. Therefore when the <hi>French</hi> Papiſts falſly charge the Proteſtants for having no certain ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, or foundation of their Faith, they do not conſider that the Proteſtants may return the charge, and ask thoſe Papiſts, where their Infallible Directors is ſince the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> was diſſolved above 120 years ago.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:63025:10"/>
               <p>If it be ſaid, that althô there is no Council now ſitting, yet Records and Writings, which contain the Canons and Decrees of Councils are yet extant, and may be conſulted. This makes a Writing capable of being a Guide or Director of our Faith, which is a thing the Romaniſts will not admit of. For when the Proteſtants affirm the written Word of God is only the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Director, then they except againſt all Writings, as inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being any certain Directors, becauſe they may be wreſted by Interpretation to bear many Senſes: And upon this account they call the Holy Scripture a Leaden Rule and a Noſe of Wax.</p>
               <p>Now for my part I cannot perceive but that the Canons and Decrees of dead Councils are liable to wreſting and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpretation as well as the Holy Scripture. Methinks the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Book is a very ſtrong proof of this; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inſtances of the like I could give, but I ſhall omit them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is notorious that the ſenſe of many Canons is exceedingly diſputable. Thus I plainly perceive upon the whole matter, that either Records of Councils are no infallible or ſufficient Guide, or if they be ſo, the Holy Scripture is much more ſuch. Whence it follows that the Proteſtants are in the right, by rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mainly upon the Scripture.</p>
               <p>Certainly, if a Writing can afford infallible direction, the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Word of God has the beſt pretence in the World to that office: Therefore the Reformed Church hath reaſon in ſome reſpect to thank the <hi>French</hi> Papiſts; for althô their pretended unerring Director is not ſufficient, yet it ſuggeſts to them where they may find out one that is very ſufficient. Such will be the conſequence of that model of an Infallible Guide which is advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and defended by the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, and by others that follow their method. But there are yet farther Inconveniences in it, enough to diſſatisfie any conſiderative perſon whatſoever. I was content (as you have heard) to paſs by the great Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie above mentioned, between the <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>French</hi> men: I could have prevailed with my ſelf to have connived at the many diſſentions under which the <hi>Gallican</hi> Divines do labour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63025:10"/>the nature and conſtitution of a General Council. Yet after all, I perceive it is impoſſible to get to an end of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, in ſo much that I am affraid I ſhall incumber the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with a tedious and long account of them. The thing that at preſent I ſhall conſider, is their diſſention concerning the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of that Infallibility which they attribute to General Councils: For ſome extend the ſuppoſed Infallibility, attending the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils aforeſaid, to all ſorts of Decrees, whether they concern Faith, or Practice; and this was the current ſenſe of the Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> 145 years ago; as appears by their concluſions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this affair, publickly agreed upon, and declared <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1542. by the Theological Faculty of that Univerſity, <hi>Articulo</hi> 22. <q rend="margQuotes">It is certain (ſay they) that General Councils lawfully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled,
<note place="margin">Certum eſt Concilium Generale le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitime Congregatam univerſalem repreſentans Eccleſiam, in Fidei &amp; Morum determinationibus er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare non poſſe,</note> and repreſenting the Univerſal Church, cannot err in Decrees concerning Faith and the Church.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But of late the <hi>Gallican</hi> Doctors ſing a new ſong; they have departed from this Opinion of their Predeceſſors, and reſtrained their imagined Infallibility of Councils only to matters of Faith. And an account of this one may find, <hi>p.</hi> 9. of the Reflections made upon the firſt Anſwer, given to the <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Repreſented.</hi> Beſides it is in every bodies mouth, that has been educated in <hi>France,</hi> that in matters of Practice, Diſcipline, or Government; General Councils are not Infallible. Thus at one ſtroke the <hi>French</hi> Doctors of theſe laſt ages have cut off, at leaſt, in nine or ten parts from the extent of that Infallibility, which their Predeceſſors 145 years ago did aſcribe to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Councils. For moſt certain it is, the Rules of Practice appertaining to Chriſtianity are (to ſpeak within compaſs) nine or ten times as many as the matters of Faith. So the modern <hi>French</hi> Clergy do hold a much leſs extended Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then what was heretofore held and taught by the Theological Faculty of <hi>Paris</hi> above mentioned: and according to the modern Poſition or Doctrin we are deſerted by the unerring Guide in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63025:11"/>much the greater part of Chriſtianity, and may err and wander in all practical Points, and ſcatter as much as any Hereticks whatever.</p>
               <p>Hereupon ſome perhaps will ſay, that although the Office of an infallible Conductor be reduced to a very ſmall compaſs, yet notwithſtanding it is better to have his help and aſſiſtance (as little as it is) than to want it. Truly there was a time when I thought ſo too: but then I conſidered, that moſt of thoſe Points controverted between Proteſtants and Papiſts are matters of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice: Therefore if the unerring direction of the Guide does not extend to practical Decrees, it follows that moſt of the points a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid have not hitherto been infallibly determined in ſavour of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Worſhip of Images, the Adoration of the Groſs, the Worſhip of Angels and Saints, the half Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, the Adoration of the Hoſt, and ſeveral other things are points of practice, and not properly matters of Faith. If it be ſaid, that the Decrees made by the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> concerning thoſe things do virtually and implicitly contain a point of Faith, by obliging us to believe the lawfulneſs or expediency of doing them, I anſwer, that the caſe of other Decrees about matters of Practice, Diſcipline, or Government is juſt the ſame: In ſo much that either all practical Decrees muſt for this reaſon be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible to matters of Faith, or elſe the Decrees concerning Image Worſhip, half Communion, and the reſt abovementioned cannot be reduced to that kind, but muſt be rank'd among matters of Practice; and ſo are not capable of any infallible Determination, if the Deſcription of the Guide given by the French Divines be true. But if any man will maintain, that all practical Decrees are reducible to matters of Faith, for the reaſon aforeſaid, then the depoſing Canon of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council is reducible to the ſame kind, and is conſequently eſtabliſhed in the Roman Church by an infallible Decree, which makes it an eſſential part of the Romiſh Church. Now this is that great inconvenience which the French Clergy do endeavour to avoid by reſtraining the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring priviledge of the Councils to matters of Faith alone. They are ſenſible that ſeveral Conſtitutions and Decrees of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63025:11"/>are prejudicial to Rights of Sovereign Princes, and injurious to the Libertis of the Gallican Church; they are aware of the great miſchief, which thoſe Canons and Decrees made for depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Kings might bring upon them if their potent Monarch ſhould perceive that ſuch Doctrines are judged eſſential to the Religion of <hi>Rome;</hi> and for that reaſon they warily reſtrain the ſuppoſed Infallibility of Councils to matters of Faith alone, and ſo give themſelves room and ſcope enough to run down the depoſing Canons &amp; Doctrines; and yet to pretend that they have an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Guide ſtill left in ſtore. But this deſign will be quite ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if practical Decrees are therefore eſteemed to be infallible becauſe they include or ſuppoſe a ſpeculative Doctrine concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lawfulneſs or expediency of things they enjoyn. For if ſuch Decrees and Conſtitutions are infallible, then they are eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial parts of the Roman Catholick Religion, even the depoſing Canons among the reſt. So that I plainly ſee the Frenchmen will be neceſſitated, by truſting to the Conduct of their infallible Guide, either to own that Image-worſhip, Invocation of Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither yet are nor indeed ever can be decreed infallibly; or elſe they muſt own the Doctrine of depoſing Princes to be infallibly decreed, which is the thing they endeavour to avoid. The latter caſe makes their Guide miſchievous and dangerous, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer makes him in a manner unſerviceable.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee what a miſerable confuſion theſe poor people have brought themſelves to, by pretending to find a viſible Judge of Controverſies incapable of Error among mortal men. They have made the greateſt part of Chriſtianity an uncertain thing (as far as in them lay) by removing it (as far as their Opinions could remove it) from its proper and natural baſis, that is, the Word of God; and by grounding it upon the teſtimony of an airy phantome, called an infallible Guide; but owned by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be liable enough to Error, and to have erred moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly in matters of the greateſt importance. They ſay, this Guide cannot be miſtaken in matters of Faith; but in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they cannot tell what they themſelves mean by that term [matters of Faith:] for although that term be of it ſelf clear enough,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63025:12"/>yet they make the ſignification of it obſcure and uncertain, by confounding matters of Faith and matters of Practice, being not able, according to their Principles (for as much as I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand) to make any clear diſtinction between them. When I was brought to this great uncertainty, and did not know on what foundation to ground my Belief, or how to underſtand certainly the Commands of God, I remembred what was ſaid <hi>Deuteron. chap.</hi> 30. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>The Commandment which I command thee this day is not hidden from thine eyes, nor is it far off. It is not in the Heaven above, that thou ſhouldſt ſay, who ſhall go up for us into Heaven, and bring it unto us, that we may hear it, and do it? neither is it beyond the Sea, that thou ſhouldſt ſay, who ſhall go over the Sea for us, and bring it unto us, that we may hear it, and do it? but the Word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou maiſt do it.</hi> And the ſame thing is repeated in the New Teſtament by St. <hi>Paul. Rom. c.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7, 8. with an application of it to the Chriſtian Diſpenſation.</p>
               <p>Having been thus taught of God, I underſtood that it was not neceſſary for me to ſeek an infallible Guide either in <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>France;</hi> God has provided ſufficient means whereby we may know his Will in all Chriſtian Countrys, without going beyond the Sea to fetch the knowledge of it from afar off. His written Word is a Guide, whoſe Veracity cannot be queſtioned; and there are means to underſtand the true ſenſe of it, which are abundantly ſufficient, and infinitely better than the Romaniſts have to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their pretended infallible Director: For that is a thing that no man certainly knows, neither what he is, nor where he is, neither how he is to be conſulted, nor how far he is to be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which, doubtleſs, are lamentable defects in a thing called a Guide. The Word of God aſſuredly ought to be our Rule. And I am reſolved to follow it, according to the Direction given me by St. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Let no man ſay to me, O!
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nemo mihi dicat, O! quid dixit Donatus, aut Parmenianus, aut Pontius, aut aliquis alius illorum? quia nec cum Catholicis Epiſcopis ſentiendumeſt, ſicubi fortè fallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut contra Canonicas Scripturas aliquid ſentiant. Aug. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit. Eccleſiae, c.</hi> 10.</note> what ſaid <hi>Donatus, Parmenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> or <hi>Pontius,</hi> or any other of them? for neither ought we to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63025:12"/>agree with Catholick Biſhops, if perhaps in ſome caſes they are ſo much miſtaken, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain Opinions contrary to the Canonical Scriptures.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> prefers the Guidance of Gods Word to the Direction of any one or more Biſhops, although account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed never ſo Catholick. It ſeemed ſtrange to me, that a matter of ſuch weight and conſequence as this is, the ſtay and prop of all Religion (as they term it,) and a thing that tends ſo much to the preſervation of Truth and Peace in the Church, ſhould not be taken notice of by the four Evangeliſts, who yet record ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things of ſmaller importance.</p>
               <p>That St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould hint nothing of it to that Church that pretends ſo mightily to it. That in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (where he takes notice of their Schiſms, one being of <hi>Paul,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of <hi>Apollos,</hi> and a third of <hi>Cephas)</hi> he did not tell them, that they ought to require <hi>Cephas</hi> his Judgment for the Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of their Differences.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, giving all diligence to mind the Chriſtians of what was needful, before his departure, ſhould forget to tell them of ſo neceſſary and ſo important an Article as this. That the Scriptures ſo frequently warn us of falſe Teachers, and falſe Prophets, that ſhould ariſe; and yet tell us nothing of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Remedy; but rather put the cure of the evil upon the pains and diligence of the Chriſtians, in trying their Spirits. That the <hi>Aſian</hi> Biſhops, in their oppoſition againſt Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> and the <hi>African</hi> in their oppoſition to Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> ſhould either not know of this priviledge of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſors, or not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it if they did. That St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> and the Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> ſhould be ſo ill inſtructed in the Faith, as not to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it; but rather ſtand out ſo ſtifly, as they did, in the caſe of Appeals. That the Popes, in the conteſt with him, ſhould be ſo ignorant of their own priviledges, as not to alledge their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibity in the Point, (which would have put a ſpeedy end to the Diſpute;) but rather take Sanctuary in a pretended Canon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63025:13"/>of the Council of <hi>Nice.</hi> That ſo many Councils ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from diſtant parts of the world, to the expences of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and the hazard of their Churches, when there was a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy ſo near at hand, as the conſulting of the infallible Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> on all occaſions. And laſtly, that the Popes themſelves ſhould ſo far disbelieve it, as to contradict and reſcind the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of one another. Theſe things ſeem to me ſuch mighty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices againſt this infallible Judg, that I know not how to anſwer them. To which I ſhall add, that inſtead of putting an end to Controverſies, and being a Cure to the evils of Chriſtendom (as is pretended,) it is the moſt expedient way to promote and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue them, by poſſeſſing that Church (which hath been the great cauſe of Diſputes) with an opinion of her own Infallibility, and conſequently rendring her incurable in her Errors, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable either of redreſſing them, or ſatisfying the Conſciences of them that diſſent from her. Conſequently St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes the ſame thing in another place more largely than above in his laſt mentioned paſſage, ſhewing nothing to have infallible Authority, except the holy Scripture, no not a General Council it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Who knows not (ſays he) that the holy Canonical Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Quis autem neſciat ſanctam Scripturam Canonicam, tam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris quam novi Teſtamenti, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſuis terminis contineri, eamque omnibus poſterioribus Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Literis ita praeponi, ut de illà omninò dubitari, ant diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptari non poſſit, utrum verum vel utrum rectum ſit quicquid in eâ ſcriptum eſſe conſtiterit? Aug. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contra Donat. cap.</hi> 3.</note> both of the old and new Teſtament, is comprehended within its own determined li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, and that it is ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the more modern Writings of Biſhops, as that it is unlawful to doubt or to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about it, or to queſtion whether any thing manifeſtly written in it be true or right?</q>
               </p>
               <p>But he then immediately after tells us, that the caſe of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Writers, of National Synods, and General Councils is quite otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Who knows not that the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63025:13"/>Writings of Biſhops,
<note place="margin">Quis autem neſciat Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Literas, quae poſt confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Canonem vel ſcriptae ſunt, vel ſcribuntur, &amp; per ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem fortè ſapientiorem cujuſlibet in eâ re peritioris, &amp; per ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum Epiſcoporum graviorem Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem, doctiorúmque Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiam, &amp; per Concilia licere reprehendi, ſi quid in eis forſan à veritate deviatum eſt, &amp; ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Concilia, quae per ſingulas Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincias vel Regiones fiant ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nariorum Conciliorum Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati, quae fiunt ex univerſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be Chriſtiano ſine ullis ambagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus cedere, ipſaque plenaria pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ora ſaepe poſterioribus emendani. Aug. ubi ſupra.</note> which either heretofore have been written, or are at preſent in compoſing, ſince the Canon of Scripture is eſtabliſhed, may lawfully be reprehended by a more ingenious Diſcourſe proceeding (it may be) from a perſon skilfuller in that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, or by the more grave Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of other Biſhops, or the Prudence of the more learned, or alſo by Councils? Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver who knows not that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial or National Synods do yield without delay to the Authority of General Councils which are gathered out of all the Chriſtian world, and that General Councils precedent in time are often corrected by them that are ſubſequent.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here we ſee, that according to St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> nothing but the Word of God is eſteemed incorrigible or infallible, not ſo much as a General Council. Therefore I am reſolved to follow this Doctrine, and to adhere to the Word of God, as my only Rule. And becauſe I find that the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this particular agrees moſt exactly with St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> for that reaſon I will henceforth embrace the Communion of that Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:63025:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE third Motive of my Converſion is my diſlike to the modern Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, and I may well call it ſo, becauſe it was diſliked by the antient Fathers, and was full 1215 Years before it could obtain the credit to be defined as an Article of Faith; for it was not defined ſuch till the Council of <hi>Lateran</hi> held the above mentioned Year under <hi>Innocent</hi> III. and the Teſtimonies of the Fathers &amp; Councils (as hereafter you ſhall ſee) are ſo decretory againſt it that the learned Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> doth ingeniouſly acknowledg it:
<note place="margin">Petr. Mar. Tract. de Euchariſt.</note> And for the juſtification of it they have been forced to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt their Logick and their Natural Philoſophy, the better to ſeaſon Young Novices for the reception of it in Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and maintain ſuch Paradoxes in them both, that if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants had the ill Fate to take them up they long ago had been hiſſed out of the Schools for defending them.</p>
               <p>Such are the propoſition of accidents exiſting without a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the poſſibility of one Body being in divers places at the ſame time: they have deſtroyed the nature of a Sacrament by taking away the Viſible Sign, and have ſtretched the words of Inſtitution to a ſenſe that many of their own Writers did not believe before it was defined; and ſome have ſince been ſo candid as to confeſs that they could not ſee the meaning of Tranſubſtantiation in the Text, if it were not for the authority of the church. They are forced to tell all men loudly to their faces, that four of their Senſes are miſtaken about their proper Object, when neither the Medium nor the Organ are indiſpoſed. That there is no Bread there at all, thô they ſee, feel, ſmell and taſte Bread. That the Senſes of this or that man, are not only miſtaken, (which is ſomewhat pardonable) but the Senſes of all mankind, at all times, and in all places, whenſoever they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63025:14"/>receive the Euchariſt, nay that they are engaged ſo fatally in the miſtake, that they are never like to be retrieved out of it, thô they uſe their utmoſt care to detect the fallacy. They are forced to contradict the common reaſon of mankind, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Propoſitions, that ſound Reaſon doth abhor in all other inſtances.</p>
               <p>Sound Reaſon tells us, that one Body can be but in one place at one time, that it muſt have <hi>partes extra partes,</hi> diſtant in ſituation, and impenetrable; that it muſt have a quantity and extenſion; that Accident cannot ſubſiſt without a Subject, that converſion of one Subſtance into another cannot be without a change in the Accidents.</p>
               <p>But in the Doctrin of Tranſubſtantiation we are taught to disbelieve all theſe Principles. The Body of Chriſt is at the ſame time in many places far diſtant from one another; it is glorious in Heaven, and on Earth ſubject to a thouſand diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; it occupies a certain place there, but in the Hoſt it takes up none, but is (in manner like a Spirit) in an indiviſible point: it moves in one place, and reſts in another: it is elevated in one place, and depreſſed in another; and all at the ſame time and ſeaſon. That the Body of Chriſt is without quantity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion; that there is length, and nothing long; breadth, and nothing broad; roundneſs, and nothing round; thickneſs, and yet nothing thick. That the Body of Chriſt doth exiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out its accidents and eſſential properties; and the accidents, of Bread and Wine without a ſubject; and yet theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents ſhall do ſtill the ſame ſeats, and ſerve a man to as uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all purpoſes as if the ſubſtance were with them; a man may ſeed upon them, and be nouriſhed with them, and have his Spirit cheered, and refreſhed with the colour, and ſmell of Wine thô he drink not a drop of it. Lo theſe are the paradoxes which the defenders of Tranſubſtantiation muſt be forced to take up for the juſtification of it; and they muſt ſtill ſeem ſo to me, till I meet with a clear and ſatisfactory anſwer to them. There was a time when I was content to ſwallow them as well as others; the prejudice of Education and Authority of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63025:15"/>Church, had ſo great an influence upon me, that I did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them as I ought; but, as by the bleſſing of God I have ſhaked off the prejudice of the one, ſo I am ſtill willing to pay a deference to the authority of the other; if it can be made good that ſhe hath authority, to impoſe things on my Belief that thwart my Senſes, and contradict common Principles of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>This monſtrous, and lately framed figment of human inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (I mean) the Doctrin of Tranſubſtantiation, is ſo far from being Primitive and Apoſtolick, that we know the time it began to be owned publickly for an Opinion; and the very Council, in which it was ſaid to be paſſed into a publick Doctrin, and by what arts it was promoted, and by what perſons it was introduced.</p>
               <p>For all the World knows, that by their own Parties, by
<note n="(a)" place="margin">In 4. lib Sentent. d. 11. q. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Scotus,</hi> by
<note n="(b)" place="margin">ibid. q. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Ocham,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. 40. in can. miſſae.</note> Biel, Fiſher</hi> Biſhop
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Cap. cont. captivit. Babyl.</note> of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whom
<note n="(e)" place="margin">De Euchar. lib. 3. cap. 23. ſect. 2. dicit.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> calls moſt acute and learned men: It was declared that the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is not expreſſed in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Bible; that in the Scriptures there is no place ſo expreſs, (as without the Churches declaration) to compel us to admit of Tranſubſtantiation; and therefore at leaſt it is to be ſuſpected of Novelty. But further, we know that it was but a diſputable Queſtion in the ninth and tenth Ages after Chriſt; that it was not pretended to be an Article of Faith till the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council in the time of <hi>Innocent</hi> III. 1215 Years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt; that ſince that pretended
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Venere quidem tunc multa in conful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationem. nec decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni tamen aperte quic quam potuit. Platina in vita Innocent III.</note> determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation divers of the chiefeſt Teachers of their own ſide have no more been ſatisfied of the ground of it than they were before, but ſtill have publickly affirmed that the Article is not expreſſed in Scripture;
<note n="(g)" place="margin">apud Suar. tom. 3. diſp. 46. ſect. 3. loc. com. lib. 3. fund. 2.</note> particularly <hi>Johannes de Baſſolis,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> and <hi>Melchior Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> beſides thoſe above reckoned: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if it was not expreſſed in Scripture it will be clear that they made their Article out of their own heads; for they could
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63025:15"/>not declare it to be there if it was not; and if it be there but obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then it ought to be taught accordingly; and at moſt it could be but a probable Doctrine, and not certain as an Article of Faith.</p>
               <p>But that we may put it paſt Argument and Probability, it is certain, That as the Doctrine was not taught in Scripture expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo it was not taught at all as a Catholick Doctrine, or as an Article of Faith by the Primitive Ages of the Church.</p>
               <p>Now in order to make this appear, we have the Confeſſions of many Authors very much eſteemed by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe authorities have been moſt exactly collected and examined by the learned Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> to whom I own my ſelf much indebted for my Converſion.</p>
               <p>For the further manifeſtation of the incontroulable truth of this point, we need no other proof but the confeſſion and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the great Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome. Scotus</hi> ſays, <hi>That before the</hi> Lateran <hi>Council Tranſubſtantiation was no Article of Faith,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſes;
<note place="margin">Lib. 3. de Euch. c. 23 Sect. unum tamen. Sum. l. 8. c. 20.</note> and <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riquez</hi> affirms that <hi>Scotus</hi> ſays, <hi>It was not antient;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> accuſes him of Ignorance, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>He talked at that rate becauſe he had not read the</hi> Roman <hi>Council under Pope</hi> Gregory VII. <hi>nor that conſent of Fathers which</hi> (to little purpoſe) <hi>he had heaped together. Rem Tranſubſtantionis Patres nè attigiſſe quidem,</hi> ſaid ſome of the Engliſh Jeſuites in Priſon. The Fathers have not ſo much as touched or medled with the matter of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation.
<note place="margin">Diſcurſ. modeſt. p. 13.</note> And in <hi>Peter Lombard</hi>'s time it was ſo far from being an Article of Faith, or Catholick Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that they did not know whether it were true or no: And after he had collected the Sentences of the Fathers in that Article, he confeſſed, He could not tell whether there was any ſubſtantial change or no. His words are theſe.
<note place="margin">L. 4. Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. diſt. 11 lit. a.</note> 
                  <hi>If it be enquired what kind of Converſion it is, whether it be formal or ſubſtantial, or another kind? I am not able to define it: only I know that it is not formal, becauſe the ſame Accidents remain, the ſame Colour and Taſt. To ſome it ſeems to be ſubſtantial, ſaying that the Subſtance is changed, that it is done eſſentially; to which the former authority ſeems to conſent:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63025:16"/>But to this Sentence others oppoſe theſe things, if the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine be ſubſtantially converted into the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, which before was not the Body, then every day ſome ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is made the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, which was not his Body before. And to day ſomething is Chriſts Body which yeſterday was not: and every day Chriſts Body is increaſed; and is made of ſuch matter, of which it was not made in the conception.</hi> Theſe are his words, which I have remarked, not only for Arguments ſake, (though it be unanſwerable;) but to give a plain demonſtration, that in his time this Doctrine was new, not the Doctrine of the Church. And this was written about
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ad Annum 1160.</note> fifty years before it was ſaid to be decreed in the <hi>Lateran</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ad Annum 1215.</note> Council: And therefore it made haſte, in ſo ſhort a time to paſs from a diſputable Queſtion to an Article of Faith. But even after the Council
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Secund. Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol. An. Dom. 1271. ſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund. Volater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranum 1335. in 4. lib. Sen. tent. diſt. 11. q. 1. ſect. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter tertium.</note> 
                  <hi>Durandus,</hi> as good a Catholick, and as famous a Doctor, as any was in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly maintained, that even after Conſecration the very matter of Bread remained; and although he ſays, <hi>that by reaſon of the Authority of the Church it is not to be held, yet it is not only poſſible it ſhould be ſo, but it implies no contradiction, that it be Chriſts Body, and yet the matter of Bread remain.</hi> And if this might be admitted, it would ſalve many difficulties which ariſe from ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the ſubſtance of Bread does not remain. But here his Reaſon was overcome by Authority, and he durſt not affirm that which alone he was able to give (as he thought) a reaſonable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of. But by this it appears that the Opinion then was but in the forge: and by all their underſtanding they could never accord it, but ſtill the Queſtions were uncertain, and the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not determined at <hi>Lateran,</hi> as it is now held at <hi>Rome.</hi> It is alſo plain, that it is a ſtranger to antiquity. <hi>De Tranſubſtantiatione <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anis in Corpus Chriſti rara eſt in antiquis Scriptoribus mentio,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Heraeſ. l. 8. verbo Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia.</note> ſaid <hi>Alphonſus à Caſtro.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">There is ſeldom mention made in the ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Tranſubſtantiating the Bread into Chriſts Body.</q> I know the modeſly and intereſt of the man, he would not have ſaid, it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63025:16"/>had been <hi>ſeldom,</hi> if he could have found it in any reaſonable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree warranted: he might have ſaid, and juſtified it, there was no mention at all of this Article in the primitive Church. And that it was a meer ſtranger to Antiquity, will not be denyed by any ſober perſon, who conſiders that it was with ſo much uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs entertained even in the corrupteſt and moſt degenerate times, and argued and unſettled almoſt 1300 years after Chriſt. And that it was ſo, will but too evidently appear by the ſtating and reſolution of this Queſtion, which we find in the Canon Law. For <hi>Berengarius</hi> was by Pope <hi>Nicholaus</hi> commanded to recant his Errors in theſe words, and to affirm,
<note place="margin">Cap. Ego Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reng. conſecr. diſt. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Verum Corpus &amp; Sanguinem Domini noſtri Jeſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti ſenſualiter non ſolum in Sacramento, ſed in veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate manibus S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cerdotum tractari, frangi, &amp; fidelium dentibus at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That the true Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſenſually not only in the Sacrament, but in truth is handled by the Prieſts hands, and broken, and grinded by the teeth of the faithful.</q> Now although this was publickly read at <hi>Rome</hi> before 115 Biſhops, and by the Pope ſent up and down the Churches of <hi>Italy, France</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi> yet this day it is renounced by the Church of <hi>Rome; and unleſs it be well expounded</hi> (ſays the Gloſs) <hi>will-lead unto Hereſie.</hi> But however this may be, it is plain they underſtood it not, as it is now decreed. But, as it happened to the <hi>Pelagians</hi> in the beginning of their Hereſie, they ſpake rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ignorantly, and eaſily to be reproved; but being aſhamed, and diſputed into a more ſober underſtanding of their Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, they ſpake more warily, but yet differently from what they ſpake at firſt. So it was and is in this Queſtion; at firſt they underſtood it not, and it was too unreaſonable in any tolerable ſenſe to make any thing of it, but experience and neceſſity hath brought it to what it is. But that this Doctrine was not the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the firſt and beſt ages of the Church, theſe following Teſtimonies do make evident.
<note place="margin">Adverſ. Marqi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. l. 4. c. 40.</note> The words of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> are theſe, <hi>The Bread being taken and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to his Diſciples, Chriſt made it his Body, ſaying, this is my Body, that is, the Figure of my Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63025:17"/>
               <p>The ſame is affirmed by <hi>Juſtin Martyr;
<note place="margin">Contra Tryph. Judae.</note> The Bread of the Euchariſt was a Figure, which Chriſt the Lord commanded to do in remembrance of his Paſſion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Dialog con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Mar. Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis ex Maximo tempore Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi &amp; Severi Imper.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> calls the Bread and the Chalice, <hi>the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Body and Blood of Chriſt.</hi> And again, <hi>that Bread which is ſanctified by the Word of God, ſo far as belongs to the matter (or ſubſtance) of it, goes into the belly,
<note place="margin">In Matt. 13.</note> and is caſt away in the ſeceſſion, or ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which to affirm of the natural and glorified Body of Chriſt were greatly blaſphemous: and therefore the Body of Chriſt which the Communicants receive, is not the Body in a natural ſenſe, but in a ſpiritual, which is not capable of any ſuch accident, as the Elements are.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">Demonſtr. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangel. l. 1. c. 1 &amp; ult. h. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>that Chriſt gave to his Diſciples the Symbols of Divine Oeconomy, commanding the Image and Type of his own Body to be made.</hi> St. <hi>Macarius</hi> ſays, <hi>that in the Church is offered Bread and Wine, the Antitype of his Fleſh, and of his Blood; and they that partake of the Bread that appears do ſpiritually eat the Fleſh of Chriſt.</hi> By which words the ſenſe of the above cited Fathers is explicated. For when they affirm, that in this Sacrament is offered the Figure, the Image, the Antitype of Chriſts Body and Blood, although they ſpeak perfectly againſt Tranſubſtantiation; yet they do not deny the real and ſpiritual preſence of Chriſts Body and Blood, which we all believe as certainly as that it is not tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, or preſent in a natural and carnal manner.</p>
               <p>The ſame is alſo fully explicated by the good St. <hi>Ephrem. The Body of Chriſt received by the faithful departs not from the ſenſible ſubſtance,
<note place="margin">De ſacris Anti och. legibus a pud Photium, l. 1. c. 229.</note> and is undivided from a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Grace. For even Baptiſm being wholly made ſpiritual, and being that which is the ſame, and proper of the ſenſible ſubſtance, I mean of Water, ſaves; and that which is born doth not periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> ſpake ſo expreſly in this Queſtion, as if he had undertaken on pupoſe to conſute the Article of <hi>Trent; Now we ſhall be partakers of the Paſchal Supper,
<note place="margin">Orat. 2. in Paſch.</note> but ſtill in figure, though more clear than in the old Law. For the legal Paſſover (I will not be afraid to ſpeak it) was an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Figure of a Figure.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63025:17"/>
               <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> affirms dogmatically,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Caeſ. contr. Haereſ. Apollinarii, cit. per Damaſc. &amp; Colect. Senten. Pp. contr. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verianos, edit per Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian. h. 23. in 1 Cor.</note> 
                  <hi>that be fore the Bread is ſanctified we name it bread, but the Divine Grace ſanctifying it by the means of the Prieſt, it is freed from the name of Bread, but is eſteemed worthy to be called the Lords Body, although the nature of Bread remains in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe very many more might be added, but inſtead of them the words of St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> may ſuffice, as being an evident con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction what was the Doctrine of the primitive Church in this Queſtion:
<note place="margin">In Pſalm. 98.</note> This great Doctor brings in Chriſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus to his Diſciples; <hi>You are not to eat this Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which you ſee, or drink that Blood which my Crucifiers ſhall pour forth. I have commended to you a Sacrament, which being ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood ſhall quicken you.</hi> And again, <hi>Chriſt brought them to a Banquet, in which he commended to his Diſciples the Figure of his Body and Blood; (for he did not doubt to ſay, this is my Body, when he gave the Sign of his Body; and that which is by all men called a Sacrifice, is the Sign of the true Sacrifice, in which the Fleſh of Chriſt, after his Aſſumption, is celebrated by the Sacrament of Remembrance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in this particular the Canon Law it ſelf, and the Maſter of the Sentences, are the beſt Witneſſes,
<note place="margin">De Conſecrat. diſt. 1. c. qui manducant, &amp;c. prima quidem, &amp;c. non hoc cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, &amp;c. quid pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</note> in both which Chollections there are divers Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies brought; eſpecially from St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> which whoſoever can reconcile with the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; may eaſily put a Civet and Dog, a Pidgeon and a Kite into couples, and make Fire and Water enter into natural and eternal Friendſhips.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> and Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> ſpeak more emphatically even to the nature of things, and the Philoſophy of the Queſtion; <hi>Chriſt honoured the Symbols and Signs</hi> (ſaith <hi>Theodoret</hi>) <hi>not changing the Nature, but to Nature adding Grace,
<note place="margin">Sentent. lib. 4. diſt. 11. dialog. 1. c. 8.</note> which Symbols are ſeen with the title of his Body and Blood.
<note place="margin">Dialog 2. c. 24.</note> For neither do the myſtical Signs recede from their Nature; for they abide in their proper ſubſtance, figure and form, and may be ſeen, touched,</hi> &amp;c. And
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63025:18"/>for a Teſtimony that will be eſteemed infallible, I alledge the words of Pope <hi>Gelaſius;
<note place="margin">De Duabus Nat. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Eutych. &amp; Neſtor. videatur Picherel. in Diſſert. de miſſa, &amp; expoſitione verbo rum Inſtitutionis coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Domini.</note> Truly the Sacraments of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, which we receive, are a divine thing, for that by them we are made partakers of the Divine Nature, yet ceaſes not to be the ſubſtance, or nature of Bread and Wine.</hi> And truly an image and ſimilitude of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of Chriſt are celebrated in the action of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries.</p>
               <p>If the Patrons of this novelty be not yet ſatisfied by what is already ſaid in reference thereunto, let them ſee and diligently mark theſe following Councils; <hi>Ancyranum anno Domini</hi> 314. <hi>Can.</hi> 2. <hi>Neocaeſarienſe anno eodem Can.</hi> 13. <hi>Nicenum</hi> 1. <hi>an.</hi> 325. <hi>in act. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Laodicenum ann.</hi> 364. <hi>Can.</hi> 25. <hi>Carthagienſe ann.</hi> 397. <hi>Can.</hi> 24. <hi>Aurelianenſe ann.</hi> 541. <hi>Can.</hi> 4. <hi>Toletanum</hi> 4. <hi>an.</hi> 633. <hi>Can.</hi> 17. <hi>Bracarenſe ann.</hi> 675, <hi>C.</hi> 2. <hi>Toletanum</hi> 16. <hi>ann.</hi> 693. <hi>C.</hi> 6. <hi>Conſtantinopolitanum in Trullo ann.</hi> 691. <hi>Can.</hi> 32. and if there be any ſhame in them, they will never brag of Antiquity to patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize them therein: for they are diametrically repugnant unto them in this behalf.</p>
               <p>Now from theſe premiſes I am not deſirous to infer any odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſequences in reproof of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but I think my ſelf bound in conſcience to ſwerve from it, and judge it my duty to give caution and admonition to all other well diſpoſed Chriſtians to do ſo likewiſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That they be not abuſed by the Rhetorical words and high expreſſions alledged out of the Fathers, calling the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Body or Fleſh of Chriſt: For we all believe it is ſo, and rejoyce in it. But the Queſtion is, after what manner it is ſo, whether after the manner of Fleſh, or after the manner of ſpiritual Grace, or ſacramental conſequence? I, with the holy Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Jo. 6.36.</note> and primitive Fathers, affirm the latter, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt the words of Scripture, and the Explication of Chriſt, affirm the former.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That they be careful not to admit ſuch Doctrines, under the pretence of being ancient, ſince although the Roman Error
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63025:18"/>had been ſo long admitted, and is ancient in reſpect of our days, yet it is an Innovation in Chriſtianity, and brought in by Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Power and Superſtition very many ages after Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I exhort them, that they remember the words of Chriſt, when he explicates the Doctrine of giving us his Fleſh for Meat, and his Blood for Drink, that he tells us,
<note place="margin">Ut ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>the Fleſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing: but the Words which I ſpeak are Spirit, and they are Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That if theſe ancient and primitive Doctors above cited ſay true, and that the Symbols ſtill remain the ſame in their natural ſubſtance and properties even after they are bleſſed, and when they are received, and that Chriſts Body and Blood are only preſent to Faith and Spirit, that then whoever attempts to give Divine Honour to theſe Symbols, or Elements, (as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does), attempts to give a Creature the due and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable propriety of God; and that then this evil paſſes fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than an error in the underſtanding, for it carrys them to a dangerous practice, which cannot reaſonably be excuſed from the crime of Idolatry.</p>
               <p>To conclude, this matter of it ſelf is an error ſo prodigiouſly great and dangerous, that I need not tell of the horrid and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Queſtions which are ſometimes handled by them of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> concerning this divine myſtery. As if a Prieſt going by a Bakers Shop, and ſaying with an Intention, <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> whether all the Bakers Bread be turned to Chriſts Body? whether a Church-mouſe does eat her Maker? whether a man by eating the conſecrated Symbols does break his faſt? for if it be Bread and Wine he does not, and if it be Chriſts Chriſts Body and Bloud naturally and properly, it is not Bread and Wine. Whether it may be ſaid, the Prieſt in ſome ſenſe is the Creator of God himſelf? whether his Power be greater than the Power of Angels and Archangels? For that it is ſo, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly affirmed by <hi>Caſſenaeus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gloria mundi 4. num. 6.</note> Whether (as a <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian</hi> Prieſt ſaid) that a Prieſt before he ſays his firſt Maſs be the Son of God, but afterward he is the Father of God, and Creator of his Body? But theſe things are too bad, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63025:19"/>therefore I love not to rake in ſo filthy channels, but give only general warning to all them whom I wiſh well, to take heed of ſuch perſons, who, from the proper conſequences of their new ſound Articles, grow too bold and extravagant, and of ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, from whence theſe and many other evil Propſitions fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently do iſſue. As the Tree is, ſuch muſt be the Fruit. But I hope it may be ſufficient to ſay, that what the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teaches of Tranſubſtantiation, is abſolutely impoſſible, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies contradictions very many, to the belief of which no Faith obligeth me, and no Reaſon can endure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the Half Communion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE fourth Motive of my Converſion is another piece of Novelty I was much diſſatisfied with, and that is, the Half Communion. And the more I inquired into the Word of God, and the Senſe of the primitive Church concerning it, the more I found cauſe to diſlike it. Certainly the common Reaſon of all men, that are Chriſtians, cannot but ſuggeſt unto them, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Command, Order and Inſtitution of Chriſt ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted extremely ſacred, and that whatever he has appointed ſhould be obſerved moſt religiouſly, without any deviation from the Rule which he hath delivered.</p>
               <p>Now upon examination I found, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had made a very unwarrantable and a ſtrange alteration in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacrament, by detaining the Cup from the people: and therefore (I hope) no rational man can blame me for rejecting Communion with her, and adhering to that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Reformed Church, where I ſaw the Command of our Saviour carefully obſerved, and his Inſtitution moſt obſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly followed. And becauſe I do here enter upon an Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> it is reaſonable I ſhould in the firſt place ſet down what I apprehend to be the Doctrine of that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63025:19"/>party concerning this matter, and then I will endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that both the Doctrine and Practice of it are repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Word of God, and to the Doctrine and Practice of the primitive Church. It is pretended by the Romaniſts, that they have made no change in any thing material or eſſential to the Sacrament: For they reſolutely affirm, that the giving of the Cup to the people is an indifferent thing, and may be done or omitted, as the Rulers of the Church ſhall judge convenient. Some of them proceed farther, and pretend that receiving the Bread alone was leſs or more the practice of all ages, ſince the beginning of Chriſtianity. Many conjectures and ſurmiſes have been invented by <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and others in order to make this ſeem likely, and yet all in vain: For many learned men of the Roman Catholick party are aſhamed of this pretence, and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly confeſs, that there never was any ſuch practice approved amongſt the Ancients.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſus à Caſtro,</hi> aſſerting the lawfulneſs of the peoples com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating in both kinds, hath theſe words, (ſaith he)</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">For I have learned from the Writings of many holy men,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nam olim per multa ſaecula ſic apud omnes Catholicos uſurpatum eſſe, ex multorum ſanctorum ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptis didicimus. Alphonſ. titul. Euchariſt. Haereſ.</hi> 13.</note> that anciently for many ages it was the cuſtom for all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques to communicate ſo.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lindanus</hi> a great maintainer of Popery affirms, that both kinds were generally received in the Euchariſt even till the year 1260. <hi>Panopliae lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 56. in theſe words,</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">I now omit other things (ſays he) which make for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to wit,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Omitto nunc alia, quae huc fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt, quod in aetatem uſque Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi Thomae</hi> 1. <hi>ann. Domini</hi> 1260. <hi>utriuſque ſpeciei Communio ferè ubique fuerir Laicis adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ſed non ubique; periculis for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè &amp; effuſi Sanguinis Domini, ſcandalis unà cum populis negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia, &amp; pietatis detrimento in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crebeſcentibus paulatim utriuſque ſpeciei Communio in unam dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neravit.</hi>
                     </note> that till the age of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> that is, till the year of our Lord 1260. the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in both kinds was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every where adminiſtred to the Laity, but not every where; perhaps dangers and ſcandals ariſing from ſpilling
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63025:20"/>the Blood of Chriſt, together with the peoples negligence, and the decay of Piety becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every day greater, the Communion of both kinds gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually degenerated into one.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albaſpinaeus,</hi> the late learned Biſhop of <hi>Orleans</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to confute ſeveral of <hi>Bellarmins,</hi> Conjectures about the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Antiquity of the Half Communion, eſpecially his fancy that the Lay-communion, a thing ſometimes mentioned by the ancient Writers, was a cuſtom of the peoples, receiving only in one kind: and upon this occaſion <hi>Albaſpinaeus</hi> hath theſe words following.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">But if we grant that which by all means we ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, to wit,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Atqui ſi detur quod concedi omninò neceſſe eſt, quo tempore Concilia &amp; Patres de Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Laicâ mentionem fecerunt, Laicos ſub utraque ſpecie commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicâſſe: ſequitur non eſſe ſub una ſpecie Communionem. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervat. cap.</hi> 4.</note> that in thoſe times, when the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Fathers made menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lay-Communion, the people did partake of both kinds: it follows, that this <hi>(i.e.)</hi> Lay-Communion is not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipating of the Sacrament under one kind.</q>
               </p>
               <p>There are two remarkable places in Cardinal <hi>Bona, lib.</hi> 2, <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>de Rebus Liturgicis,</hi> to prove that the Communion in one kind was not practiſed till the year 1200. and that all the precedent ages had the contrary practice, and gave both kinds to the people publickly. He pretends beſides, but indeed without any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable ground, that the Half Communion was privately practiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in thoſe ages. Theſe are his ſayings,</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">It is certain (ſays he) that all perſons in all places,
<note place="margin">Certum eſt quippe omnes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim Clericos &amp; Laicos, viros &amp; mulieres ſub utraque ſpecie ſacra myſteria antiquitùs ſumpſiſſe cum ſolemni eorum Celebrationi ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant &amp; offerebant, &amp; de Oblatis participabant.</note> Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and people, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, did anciently receive the holy myſteries in both kinds when they were preſent at the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63025:20"/>publick Celebration, when they offered, and did partake of the Offerings.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And a little after,</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">For always and every where,
<note place="margin">Semper enim &amp; ubique, ab Eccleſiae primordiis uſque ad ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum duodecimum, ſub ſpecii Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; Vini communicârent fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, caepitque paulatim ejus ſaecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li initio uſus calicis obſoleſcere.</note> from the infancy of the Church till the 12th age, the faithful received the Communion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both kinds, of Bread and Wine; and the cuſtom of the Cup in the beginning of that age began by little and little to be diſuſed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee by the Teſtimonies already produced, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Cup from the people was no ancient practice, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan about 460 years ago. Theſe Authors here cited being Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are a ſufficient proof of this, and many more of the ſame Perſwaſion might be brought to confirm the ſame, which at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent I omit, that I may ſhun tediouſneſs. But the thing which upon examination I found my ſelf obliged principally to conſider, was not only what had been the ancient practice in this matter, but alſo what the reaſon &amp; ground was which moved the holy Fathers and the primitive Church generally (as well Laity as Clergy) to believe themſelves moſt ſtrictly bound to receive both kinds. For that they had ſuch a Belief, the Authorities which I ſhall hereafter alledge will convincingly demonſtrate, and the reaſon and ground of this their Perſwaſion was the Command and Inſtitution of Chriſt. He had ordered in the Goſpel, that all ſhould drink of the Cup, and they, with great Piety and Reverence to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, accounted themſelves all obliged to do what he enjoyned them.</p>
               <p>This certainly is nothing but what ought to be done. And I heartily wiſh the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had retained the like veneration and pious regard for the Command of Chriſt; I ſhould then have found no cauſe to blame her in this particular.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe I have here in effect aſſerted, that the Command of Chriſt concerning the Sacrament was that which had influence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63025:21"/>upon the Chriſtians of the eldeſt ages; I ſhall in the firſt place produce the Precept, and then ſubjoin immediately the Senſe of Antiquity to it, which will manifeſt that they thought the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ariſing from the Divine Precept did extend to all Believers without any diſcrimination; and if this be effectually performed, I ſuppoſe, it will be unneceſſary to advertiſe the Reader, that the ſame apprehenſions concerning the neceſſity of receiving in both kinds ought to take place at all times, and in all Chriſtian Societies. The conſequence of which is, that the Roman Church is a notorious tranſgreſſor of Divine Law in this reſpect; and that the pretended indifferency of giving the Cup to the people, or withholding of it, is a falſe ſuppoſition.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour, when he firſt appointed this Sacrament, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Command, <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.27. that all ſhould drink of the Cup; and after his Reſurrection he reinforced all the Precepts which he had given to his Diſciples, and conſequently this amongſt the reſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. ſaying, <hi>Go, teach all Nations; baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt; teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you.</hi> We ſee hence how expreſs our Saviours words are, that all Nations ſhould be taught to obſerve whatever he commanded his Diſciples; who would think (if he ſaw it not before his eyes) that any Society of Chriſtians, that will needs be called the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, ſhould avowedly trample under foot this manifeſt Command of God? They are ſo far from teaching all Nations to obſerve what Chriſt commanded his Diſciples, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly teach the quite contrary. Our Saviour ſaid, <hi>Drink ye all of it.</hi> No, ſays the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> all ſhall not drink of it, but a few ſhall, that is, conſecrating Prieſts. One would ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that theſe Texts of holy Scripture above mentioned ſhould make a deep impreſſion upon all men that pretend to have any regard for the Laws of God, and they did ſo till 1200 years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, when the practice of detaining the Cup from the people began firſt to be introduced by a corrupt cuſtom, and was long afterwards eſtabliſhed by Pope <hi>Martin</hi> V. in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> So new and late is this Point of Popery, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63025:21"/>it was not conciliarly decreed till about 272 years ago. And yet nothing is more uſual with the Roman Catholicks, than to brag of the Antiquity of their Religion. I ſhall have an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity hereafter of conſidering this late Decree of Pope <hi>Martin,</hi> when I come to produce the ancient Canon of Pope <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> made near 1200 years ago, expreſly repugnant, and contary to this late Decree of <hi>Martin:</hi> For <hi>Gelaſius</hi> declares receiving in one kind to be ſacrilegious.</p>
               <p>At preſent I ſhall proceed to alledge the Teſtimonies of the ancient Fathers, to ſhew that they underſtood our Saviours words <hi>[Drink ye all of this]</hi> agreeably to the Senſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church of <hi>England;</hi> that is, ſo as to account all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, without exception, obliged to partake of the Cup. But by the way, I cannot but obſerve, that <hi>Paſchaſius Corbeienſis,</hi> a man of great credit in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for his Invention of Chriſts corporeal Preſence in the Hoſt, about the year 830. did expound the words above mentioned, contrary to the Senſe of the preſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in favour of the Proteſtants. His expreſſions are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">It is Chriſt that breaks this Bread,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chriſtus eſt qui frangit hunc Panem, &amp; per manus Miniſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tribuit credentibus. Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter &amp; calicem porrigit eis, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens, accipite, &amp; bibite ex hoc omnes tam Miniſtri, quam reliqui Credentes. Paſchaſ. be Coena Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, cap.</hi> 14.</note> and by the hands of the Miniſters delivers it to the Believers. Likewiſe he gives them the Cup, ſaying, <hi>take, and drink ye all of this,</hi> both the Miniſters and other Believes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here we ſee <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> makes the Command to extend to all without any difference; and it is a wonder to me, why the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks do follow this man ſo zealouſly in his Invention of the corporeal Preſence of Chriſt in the Euchariſtical Bread, and will not admit of his Interpretation of this Command of Chriſt, that all Believers ſhould drink of the Cup.</p>
               <p>But there are much more ancient and authentick Authors, who underſtood our Saviours words according to the Senſe of the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Teſtimonies hereafter
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63025:22"/>follow, and that in reference of proving that the Members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of do not expound Scripture according to their own private Judgment, as it is falſely imputed to them by the wretched Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>Pax Vobis,</hi> Mr. <hi>Manby</hi> and others, who (as I plainly find) never underſtood any thing of the Doctrine of this Church concerning the Interpretation of Scripture.</p>
               <p>The firſt ancient Writer, whoſe Authority I intend to make uſe of, is S. <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> one that lived not long after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick age, and loſt his Life for the Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith. He in his ſecond Apology gives an account to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the method and manner of Divine Service amongſt the Chriſtians, and coming to give an account of the Lords Supper, he does it thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">They that are called Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons among us do diſtribute to every one preſent,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Qai apud nos vocantur Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni diſtribuunt unicuique prieſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ut participent de Pane, &amp; Vino &amp; Aquâ benedictis. Juſtin. Apol</hi> 2.</note> that they may partake of the conſecrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Bread, and Wine, and Water.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It is remarkable, that he ſays, the Deacons gave both kinds to every one preſent, and a little after he tells us, they did ſo; becauſe our Saviour in the Goſpel commanded them to do ſo. <q rend="margQuotes">For (ſays he) the Apoſtles in the Books written by them,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nam Apoſtoli in Commentariis à ſe ſcriptis, quae Evangelia vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur, ita ſibi praecepiſſe Jeſum tradiderunt. Juſtin. Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>ubi ſupra.</hi>
                     </note> which are called the Goſpels, have taught us, that Jeſus commanded them to do ſo.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmin</hi> pretends that this laſt expreſſion of S. <hi>Juſtin,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Command of Chriſt, hath only relation to the Gonſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, not to the Adminiſtration of the Sacrament. But any man by reading the place will ſind the Cardinals words to be ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs: For the Command of Chriſt is offered by S. <hi>Juſtin</hi> as the reaſon of the whole procedure in celebrating the Sacrament, and not as particularly reſpecting the Conſecration of the Elements.</p>
               <p>The ſecond an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ient Author, whoſe Teſtimony I ſhall produce as an uncontroulable Evidence in this behall, is St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who flouriſhed principally about the Yeat 250. and not many Years
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63025:22"/>after was put to death for his Religion. This Holy Martyr, in his Epiſtle to <hi>Caecilius,</hi> reprehends the <hi>Aquarians,</hi> that were He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, ſo called, becauſe in the Conſecration and Adminiſtration of this Holy Sacrament of our Lords Supper they made no uſe of Wine, but uſed Water in ſtead of it. Now Sr. <hi>Gyprian</hi> reproves theſe <hi>Aquarians</hi> upon two accounts: Firſt in that they offered to Conſecrate without Wine; and ſecondly, in that they gave no Wine to the People; and in both reſpects he taxes them with a very great tranfgreſſion of the command and appointment of our Saviour. The former miſcarriage and irrogularity of the <hi>Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> doth not concern the Roman Catholicks; becauſe they uſe Wine when they Conſecrate: But in the ſecond point they are like the <hi>Aquarians,</hi> and therefore do fall under the ſame cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with them. Let us hear what St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſays concerning this whole affair: He begins the Epiſtle by telling <hi>Caecilius,</hi> That although many Reverend Biſhops did exactly obſerve our Lords Tradition (for ſo calls he the Command or Inſtitution of Chriſt) yet (ſays he) <q rend="margQuotes">becauſe ſome out of Ignorance or ſimplicity in conſecrating the Cup of our Lord,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tamen quoniam quidam vel igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranter, vel ſimpliciter in Calice Dominico ſanctificando &amp; plebi miniſtrando, non faciunt quod Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſtas Dominus &amp; Deus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (hujus Sacrificii Auctor &amp; Doctor) fecit, &amp; docuit: religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſum pariter, ac neceſſarium duxi, de hoc ad vos literas facere at ſiquis in iſto errore adhuc tenea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur veritatis luce perſpectâ ad radicem &amp; originem Dominicae Traditionis revertatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Cypr. Epiſt.</hi> 63. <hi>Pamilianae editionis.</hi>
                     </note> and in adminiſtring it to the People, do not do that which Jeſus Chriſt our Lord God (the Teacher and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Sacrifice) did, and taught: I judged it to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to good Conſcience, and neceſſary to write to you about this matter; that if any one be yet poſſeſſed with this Error, he may, by ſeeing the Light of Truth, return to the root and original of our Lords Tradition.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And thus having eſtabliſht his foundation, namely that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to be done contrary to the Inſtitution of Chriſt:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63025:23"/>in the firſt part of his Epiſtle he proves the neceſſity of uſing Wine in the Conſecration of the Sacrament; but in the later part he comes to conſider the great inconvenience and miſchief to the people that enſued from their being deprived of the Cup. And that which he chiefly takes notice of, was a great decay and failure of Chriſtian Courage, occaſioned (as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes) by this depravation of the Sacrament. For in times of Perſecution ſome learned (from the <hi>Aquarians</hi>) to abſtain from drinking the Conſecrated Wine, leaſt the ſmell of it ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover that they have been at the Chriſtian Meetings in the Mornings: St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> Words are theſe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caeterum omnis Religionis, et ve ritatis Diſciplina ſubvertitur, niſi id, quod ſpiritualiter praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur, fideliter obſervetur, niſi ſi ſacrificiis matutinis hoc quis ve retur, ne per ſaporem vini redo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat ſanguinem Chriſti: ſic ergo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incipit in perſecutionibus a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione Chriſti fraternitas retardari dum in oblationibus diſcit de ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine ejus, et cruore confundi Cyp. Ep.</hi> 63. <hi>ubi ſupra.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">But the diſcipline and good order of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Truth is overthrown, unleſs what was ſpiritually commanded be faithfully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. But perhaps the caſe is, that ſome perſons in the Morning Sacrifices (or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) are afraid, leaſt by the ſavor of Wine they ſhould ſmell of Chriſts Blood, and ſo by this means our Chriſtian Brethren in times of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion begin to be ſlack, or backward in ſuffering for Chriſt, while at the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacrament they learn to be aſhamed of Chriſts Blood.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And a little after the ſame Author ſays,
<note place="margin">Quomodo autem poſſumus propter Chriſtem ſanguinem fundere qui ſanguinem Chriſti erubeſcimus bibere.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">How can we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſham'd to drink the Blood of Chriſt, ſpill our Blood for Chriſts ſake.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides in another Epiſtle the ſame <hi>S. Cyp.</hi> writing to <hi>Cornelius</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:63025:23"/>the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> concerning the reſtoring of certain delinquent Brethren (who in times of Perſecution had fallen into Idolatry, but by Repentance deſerved to be reconciled to the Church) urges the neceſſity of their being admitted into Communion; becauſe that ſince new Troubles and Perſecutions were coming on, it would be neceſſary to arm and fortifie all Believers with the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; and he inſiſts particularly upon the neceſſiy of giving them the Sacramental Cup. His ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions are theſe that follow,</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">For after what a ſtrange manner do we teach and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite them to loſe their Blood in confeſſing the Name of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nam quomodo docemus aut provocamus eos in confeſſione No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis Chriſti ſanguinem ſuum fundere, ſi eis militaturis San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem Chriſti denegamus? aut quomodo ad Martyrii poculum idoneos facimus, ſi eos priùs ad bibendum in Eccleſiâ poculum Domini jure Communicationit non admittimus? Cyp. Ep</hi> 54. <hi>Edit. Pamel.</hi>
                     </note> if we deny the Blood of Chriſt to them that are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to undergo ſuch a warfare? And how do we make them fit for the Cup of Martyrdom, if we do not admit them firſt by the right of Communion to drink our Lords Cup in the Church?</q>
               </p>
               <p>It is obſervable that S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> here pleads for the peoples re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Cup from the right of Communion, that is, from the right which accrewed to every one, by his being made a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the viſible Church.</p>
               <p>By this paſſage, and the reſt before cited, it appears abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what the Judgment of this holy Martyr was, that he thought all Chriſtians obliged to receive the conſecrated Wine, and that the omiſſion of it was a tranſgreſſion of our Lords Commandment, and the deſtruction of ſeveral Chriſtian virtues, eſpecially of that courage and reſolution wherewith all Believers ought openly to profeſs the Name of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I might produce many more ancient Witneſſes of great credit, to make good what is here by me affirmed, but I ſhall content my ſelf, for brevitys ſake, with two others, whoſe Authority
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63025:24"/>doubtleſs ought to be paſt all exception with the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks; becauſe they were Popes or Biſhops of <hi>Rome:</hi> for anciently the Title of Pope was given to any eminent Biſhop. The firſt of theſe is <hi>Leo,</hi> the firſt of that name that was Biſhop in <hi>Rome;</hi> but before I produce his Teſtimony, it is neceſſary to obſerve that although his words are levelled againſt the <hi>Manichees,</hi> who ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly abhorred Wine; and therefore avoided receiving the Sacramental Cup: yet <hi>Leo</hi>'s words do abundantly ſhew what his Judgment was concerning that neceſſity, which as he thought did lye indiſpenſibly upon all Communicants to partake of the myſtical Blood of Chriſt; <q rend="margQuotes">Conſequently (ſays he) when they venture to be preſent at our myſteries,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cumque ad tegendam infidelita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſuam noſtris audeant inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe myſteriis, ita in Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum Communione ſe temperant, ut interdum tutius lateant; ore indigno Chriſti Corpus accipiunt, Sanguinem autem Redemptionis noſtrae haurire omninò declinant; quod ideò veſtram ſcire volumus ſanctitatem, ut nobis hujuſmodi homines his manifeſtentur indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis; &amp; quorum fuerit depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſa ſacrilegia ſimulatio, notati, &amp; proditi à Sanctorum ſocieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Sacerdotali Authoritate pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantur. Serm.</hi> 4. <hi>in Quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſ.</hi>
                     </note> they after ſuch manner do comport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in partaking of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, that ſometimes they very ſafely paſs undiſcerned; with an unprepared mouth they receive the Body, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together avoid the drinking of the Blood of our Redemption, which I would have you, holy Brethren, therefore to take no tice of, that by theſe indications ſuch men as theſe may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to us; and that they, whoſe ſacrilegious diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſound out by being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and detected, may be driven from the ſociety of the Saints by the Power of the Church.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it is manifeſt to any man of reaſon, that St. <hi>Leo</hi> lookt upon this practice of the <hi>Manichees</hi> as a moſt wicked and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious thing, and he decrees no leſs a penalty for it than Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63025:24"/>Now it cannot be their inward and inviſible ſuperſtition that he would have notice taken of, but it muſt be their external comportment in avoiding the conſecrated Wine. Moreover if receiving the Cup had been an indifferent thing, and eſteemed ſo in <hi>Leo</hi>'s age, then the omiſſion or declining of it, would have been no diſtinctive mark to diſcover the <hi>Manichees</hi> from the Orthodox or regular Communicants: For both might have done the ſame thing, and ſo the <hi>Manichees</hi> would have gone undiſcovered. Hence I could not but conclude that <hi>Leo,</hi> and all Orthodox believers of his time, were of the ſame judgment in this point, with the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſince that Reverend Biſhop lookt upon receiving the Cup, as a certain ſign of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and true Chriſtian, and eſteemed the contrary practice an infallible marke of a deteſtable and ſacrilegious Heretick.</p>
               <p>And I am exceedingly confirmed in this Opinion, becauſe I find that Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> (one who ſate in the Epiſcopal Chair of <hi>Rome</hi> about Thirty years after <hi>Leo</hi>'s death) hath in a moſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, ſolemn, and authentick manner declared the neceſſity of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving in both kinds and the contrary practice to be ſacrilegious; For he made a Canon againſt the corrupt cuſtom of Receiving in one kind, which ſome ſuperſtitious people were then endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to introduce: And this very Canon is to be found in <hi>Gratians</hi> Body of the Canon Law. <hi>De Conſecrat. diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12. It is in the Acts of the Councils. It is alſo in the Annals of <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Baronius ad annum</hi> 496. But in ſhort there is no doubt of its being the true and genuine Canon of <hi>Gelaſius</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no man can rationally deny this to be a very convincing proof; that the judgment and practice of the ancient Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> was directly contrary to that of the Modern Biſhops, and Church thereof. I ſhall here produce the words of the Canon it ſelf; that the impertiall Reader may judge whether I had not reaſon to conclude, that the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church is guilty of Novelties, and that the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> does punctually follow the ſenſe of Antiquity.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">But we find (ſays he) that ſome who having received the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63025:25"/>portion of the Holy Body, do abſtain from the Cup of the Blood.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Comperimus autem quod qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam-ſumpta tantummodo Corpus ſacri portione, â Calice Cruo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris abſtineant: qui proculdubio, quoniam neſcio qua ſuperſtitione docentur obſtringi, aut integra ſacramenta percipiant; aut ab integris arceautur, quia diviſio vnius ejuſdemque myſterii ſine grandi ſacrilegio non poteſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire. Gratian. de conſecrat. diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> Let theſe men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all controverſy (becauſe they are informed againſt; as perſons poſſeſt with I know not what ſuperſtition) either receive the whole Sacrament or abſtaine from the whole: for a diviſion or parting of the one and the ſame miſtery cannot come to paſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out very great ſacriledge.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This ancient Canon (I find) hath given very ſtrange diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance to the modern Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> great ſtir hath been to avoid the force of it; if it were poſſible to be done: And becauſe it cannot be denyed, that this Canon or Decree was made by <hi>Gelaſius</hi> almoſt 1200 years ago. Therefore many interpretations have been deviſed to make it reconcilable, and conſiſtent with their preſent practice of detaining the Cup from the People.</p>
               <p>The firſt device is to imagine and ſuppoſe without any manner of ground in the world, that this Decree only reſpects the Prieſts conſecrating the Hoſt. Thus we find the Author of the Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations upon <hi>Gratian</hi> endeavouring to eſcape the difficulty. But undoubtedly neither the Proteſtants, nor any rational man, hath any reaſon to regard this vain and idle ſuppoſition. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when ſo eminent a man, as Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> hath aſſured us; that this is a ſenſeleſſe and fooliſh ſolution. He calls it <hi>frigidam ſolutionem ad annum</hi> 496 <hi>num.</hi> 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21. And ſays; <hi>he rejects it, and hath no need of ſuch foolery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there is another evaſion which is commonly made uſe of by the Romaniſt, in order to elude the force of this Canon; and becauſe this evaſion is moſt in vogue amongſt them therefore particularly I did conſider it.</p>
               <p>Many of their controvertiſts, do pretend that the ancient De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of <hi>Gelaſius</hi> was only temporary and occaſional, built upon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63025:25"/>the condition of the times; when it was made. <hi>And therefore</hi> (ſay they) <hi>it might be abrogated without any violation of Divine law; when the reaſon of it, by the change of the times, was removed.</hi> Now it is pretended, that the reaſon or cauſe of it was this; <hi>In the age of</hi> Gelaſius (ſay they) <hi>the Church was exceedingly peſtered with a copious number of diſſembling</hi> Manichees, <hi>who had a mind to be accounted Catholicks; yet out of a ſuperſtitious averſion to Wine, abſtained from the Cup in the Sacrament.</hi> And this, if we believe them, was the cauſe and reaſon of the Decree againſt receiving in one kind, and not any Divine Precept enjoyning both.</p>
               <p>This I narrowly examined, and found it to be more idle and inſignificant than the former, which Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> called <hi>ſenſeleſs and fooliſh.</hi> For whatever the condition of thoſe times was, the principal reaſon of the Canon is incorted into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non it ſelf, and it is this following, <hi>[Becauſe a parting of one and the ſame myſtery cannot come to paſs without very great Sacriledge.]</hi> Now I muſt beg leave of my old Friends, to tell them that this is no temporary or mutable reaſon: certainly, <hi>not to commit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge</hi> is a thing of unchangeable and perpetual obligation, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has it any dependence upon the condition of any Age or Time: For let the Times change never ſo much, it will never be lawſul to commit Sacriledge, and ſuch is communicating in one kind alone, if Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> may be believed.</p>
               <p>Thus it is plain, that this ancient Decree is directly contrary to the late conſtitutions of the Roman Church, and theſe eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, invented in order to make it ſeem reconciliable, have not any plauſible colour of reaſon. Therefore I doubt not, but the judicious and impartial Reader will be ſatisfied, that it is neceſſary for all Chriſtians that come to the Lords Supper, to partake of it in both kinds; and that this neceſſity ariſes from the Command of our Saviour, enjoining all to drink of the Cup. The ancient Fathers did ſo believe, and teach, as the Authorities already cited do clearly and ſatisfactorily manifeſt. Herein I have <hi>Lindanus</hi> agreeing with me (though he was a great Defender of Popery) in theſe words, when he had firſt ſhewn what the Opinion of the old Writers was, ſaid,</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:63025:26"/>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">After this manner the ancient Fathers, chiefly St. <hi>Leo,
<note place="margin">Hunc igitur in modum illam ve tuſtiſſimam, planéque Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam utriuſque ſpeciei Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem conſervatam atque obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam populo Chriſtiano cupiebant priſci Patres, Divus Leo, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſius, &amp; Patres in Concilio Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronenſi.</note> Gelaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and the Fathers in the Council of <hi>Tours</hi> did deſire that that moſt ancient and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together Apoſtolical Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in both kinds might be preſerved and obſerved by the Chriſtian people.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly. That the Reader may the better compare this ancient Doctrine and Practice with the novel and late Rule ſet up by the Romaniſts, it is neceſſary that I produce the Canon made by Pope <hi>Martin</hi> V. in the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> about 272 years ago, which forbids adminiſtring the Cup to the people. Becauſe the Canon is long I ſhall only produce two clauſes of it, and any man that pleaſes may conſult the whole, and judge whether I do any wrong. I am ſure, I intend to deliver nothing but what is truth. After a Preface containing the reaſons of their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings it is ſaid, <q rend="margQuotes">The holy General Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> defines,
<note place="margin">Concilium ſacrum generale Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantienſe definit, quod licet Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus poſt Caenam inſtituerit, &amp; ſuis Diſcipulis adminiſtraverit ſub utraque Panis &amp; Vini ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, venerabile hoc Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum (tamen hoc non obſtante) &amp;c. Acta Conc. Conſtant. edit. Labb.</note> that altho' Chriſt did inſtitute this vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sacrament after Supper, and adminiſter it under both kinds, of Bread and Wine, to his Diſciples, (yet <hi>hoc non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante)</hi> notwithſtanding this, it is firſt decreed, that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould not be celebrated after Supper.</q> And then ſome things being brought in by way of Preamble, to put a blind upon the matter, <q rend="margQuotes">It is alſo decreed, that the cuſtom of giving only one kind to the people (tho' contrary to Chriſts Inſtitution, and the Practice of the primitive Church) ſhould thenceforth be accounted Law.</q> In the latter part of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non there is a clauſe directly oppoſite to the Decree of <hi>Gelaſius</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63025:26"/>above mentioned. For whereas that ancient Pope had declared, that receiving in one kind could not be without Sacriledge, the Canon of <hi>Conſtance</hi> contradicts him after this manner; <q rend="margQuotes">Therefore to ſay the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this cuſtom, or Law,
<note place="margin">Quapropter dicere quod hanc con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinem, vel legem obſervare ſit ſacrilegum, cenſeri debet er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneum.</note> is ſacrilegious, ought to be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed erroneous.</q> Then it ſeems the Decree of <hi>Gelaſius</hi> ought to be judged erroneus. For that Decree affirms the cuſtom or law about receiving in one kind to be ſacrilegious, as has heretofore been abundantly ſhewn.</p>
               <p>Thus having found the Practice and Doctrine of the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> contrary and repugnant to the Word of God, and to the Judgment of ancient Authors, of which ſome were Popes, publickly enacting the direct oppoſite to what was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decreed at <hi>Conſtance;</hi> I could not but conclude that I was in no right way: And therefore took up a reſolution to adjoin my ſelf to the Proteſtant Church, where I ſaw the Command of Chriſt carefully obſerved, and the Sacrament in both kinds given to the people, according to his Inſtitution.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of Image-Worſhip.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe fifth Motive of my Converſion is the Uſe, or rather the Abuſe of Images. There is none that pretends to the leaſt knowledge of Antiquity, but knows that the Worſhip of Graven Images is far from being either a Chriſtian, Apoſtolick, Primitive or Catholick Practice: and yet the Papiſts give to graven Images the Worſhip due to God, to Chriſt and his Saints, tho they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend otherwiſe. We need not enquire what actions they ſuppoſe fit to be uſed in their Image-Worſhip: For theſe appear in their publick Proceſſions, their Incenſings, and Pilgrimages, their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Vows made unto them. Certainly the Worſhip of a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63025:27"/>graven Image is plainly and frequently forbidden in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as you may read in the Commandments uttered with Gods own Mouth, with Thundring and Lightning on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> viz. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image, nor the likeneſs of any thing, that is in Heaven above, or in the Earth beneath, or in the Water under the Earth; thou ſhalt not how down to them, nor worſhip them.</hi> Which Thunder from Heaven the Guides of the Romiſh Church diſcerning to threaten vehemently their dreadful Idolatry which daily they commit, thought fit in wiſdom to conceal the knowledge of the ſecond Commandment from the people, by excluding it from the Decalogue, and divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the tenth into two. And notwithſtanding their Image-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is ſo infinite a Scandal to the Jews and Turks, and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to Chriſtianity it ſelf among all ſtrangers that live with them, and obſerve their Rites, and that it cannot in the leaſt be pretended to be lawful, but with the laborious artifices of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Airy and Metaphyſical Diſtinctions, which the people who moſt need them do leaſt underſtand; yet they uſe theſe and many other miſerable ſhifts, and ſilly evaſions, whereby they labour to darken the Light of the true Catholick Doctrine in this point, as has been manifeſted by many (of great capacity) to the full, in their Comments on <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.15, 16. and other places of Scripture, where you may ſee that the adoring of the very true God himſelf in or by an Image cometh within the compaſs of Idolatry, which the Word of God condemneth: and therefore that this whole Doctrine and Practice is contrary to the Law of God I need not tell you. Let us hear what the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians held concerning Images, firſt in their Councils, ſecondly in the Writings of the primitive Fathers.</p>
               <p>Firſt then as to their Councils; For keeping of Pictures out of the Churches, the Canon of the <hi>Eliberine</hi> Council (held in <hi>Spain</hi> about the time of <hi>Conſtantine the Great)</hi> gives this directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>It is our Will, that Pictures ought not to be in the Church, leſt that which is worſhiped or adored ſhould be painted on the Walls.</hi> Which words have ſo troubled the Wits of the late Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that <hi>Melchior Canus</hi> ſcrupleth not only to accuſe the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63025:27"/>Council of Impudency, but alſo of Impiety for making ſuch a Law. In a Council of ſeveral Biſhops in the year of our Lord 730. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Leo</hi> the Emperor, titled <hi>Iconomachus,</hi> Images were ſolemnly condemned. And in another Council held at <hi>Conſtantinople ann.</hi> 755. or thereabouts, under the Reign of <hi>Conſtantine Copronymus,</hi> with great ſolemnity they were alſo condemned.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the ſeveral Decrees of theſe Councils enacted againſt the Idolatrous Worſhip of Images, the ſecond Council of <hi>Nice</hi> advanced Image-Worſhip. And that indeed was very like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be the product of a Council aſſembled by that moſt wicked Empreſs <hi>Irene,</hi> who was bred and educated in Heatheniſm, and probably continued a Heathen in her heart all the days of her life, if we may judge of her Religion by her actions. Certainly no perſon, that had any ſenſe of Chriſtianity, would ever do the things that ſhe did. Now by the Authority and Intereſt of this impious Woman, and by the procurement of Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> I. this Decree for Image-worship was obtained.</p>
               <p>But this Decree, altho' it was not by many degrees ſo groſs as what was afterwards invented by the Schoolmen of the Popiſh Communion, yet was rejected as repugnant to the Doctrine of the Church of God by the Princes and Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> about the year 792. and afterwards by <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> and the Biſhops of <hi>Italy, France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> which by his appointment were gathered together in the Council of <hi>Frankford</hi> in the year 794.</p>
               <p>Thus much I thought needful to be alledged againſt the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images from the Authority of Councils, ſome of which have better pretences to be accounted General, than either the ſecond of <hi>Nice,</hi> or that of <hi>Trent</hi> can pretend to.</p>
               <p>But then in the ſecond place, if we conſider the Teſtimonies of the Fathers, we ſhall find them plain againſt Image worſhip. The ſact of <hi>Epiphanius</hi> rending the Veil that hung in the Church of <hi>Anablatha</hi> is effectual, to demonſtrate what an abomination it was in his days, and in his opinion, to worſhip Images; which himſelf in his Epiſtle to <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> (tranſlated by St. <hi>Hierom</hi> out of Greek into Latin) does thus explain.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:63025:28"/>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">I found there (ſays he) a Veil hanging at the door of the Church dyed,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Inveni ibi Velum pendens in foribus ejuſdem Eccleſiae tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, atque depictum, &amp; habens Imaginem quaſt Chriſti, vel San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti cujuſdam; non enim ſatis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini cujus Image fuerit. Cum ergo hoc vidiſſem in Eccleſiâ Chriſti contra Auctoritatem Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturarum hominis pendere Imagi nem, ſcidi idud, &amp; magis dedi conſilium cuſtodibus ejuſdem loci ut pauperom mortuum eo obvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent &amp; efferrent. Epiph. Ep. ad Joan. Hieroſolym. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Hieron. Ep.</hi> 60.</note> and paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and having the Image as it were of Chriſt, or ſome Saint; for I do not well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member whoſe Image it was. When therefore I ſaw this, that <hi>contrary to the Athority of the Scriptures,</hi> the image of a man was hanged up in the Church of Chriſt, I cut it, and gave counſel to the Keepers of the place, that they ſhould wrap and bury ſome poor dead man in it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And afterwards he intreated the Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> under whoſe Government this Church was, <q rend="margQuotes">To give charge thereafter,
<note place="margin">Praecipere in Eccleſia Chriſti iſtiuſmodi Vela, quae contra no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram Religionem veniunt, non appendi. Epiſt. Epiphanii, ubi ſupra.</note> that ſuch Veils as theſe, which are repugnant to our Religion ſhould not be hanged up in the Church of Chriſt.</q> Had this holy Father now been ariſed from the dead, and had ſeen the great number of Images not only hung in Churches, and Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of them of the Communion of <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo worſhiped and adored relatively (as their Diſputants term it,) how much, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader, think you, would he be amazed and aſtoniſhed hereat? would he not rather judge them to be the Churches of <hi>Baal,</hi> than of Chriſt? And yet theſe people brag of Antiquity after this, and pretend to rely on the Authority of ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in aſſerting the Lawfulneſs of Image-worſhip.</p>
               <p>Let us hear in the next place what <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Imagines ſacrae, quibus inaniſſimi homines ſerviunt, omni Senſu ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, quia terra ſunt. Quis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem non intelligat nefas eſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum animal curvari, ut adoret torram, quae ideo ſubjecta eſt, ut calcanda à nobis non adoranda ſit? Quare non eſſe dubium, quin Religio nulla fit ubicunque ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachrum eſt — Divini autem nibil eſt niſi in caeleſtibus rebus; carent ergo Religione ſimulachra quia nihil poteſt eſſe caeleſte in ea re quae fit ex terrâ. Lactant. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 17, <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Thoſe conſecrated Images (ſays he) which vain men do ſerve, want all Senſe, becauſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63025:28"/>they are earth. Now who is there, that underſtands not that it is unfit for an upright creature to be bowed down that he may worſhip the earth, which for this cauſe is put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our feet that it may be trodden upon, not worſhiped by us? Wherefore there is no doubt, but that there is no Religion wherever there is an Image— There is nothing that is godly, but conſiſts in heavenly things. Therfore I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages are things that have nothing to do with Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (or they are void of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) becauſe nothing that is heavenly can be in that thing which is made of earth.</q>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> affirms, that in his days the Church was an utter ſtranger to any thing like Images. He tells us, <q rend="margQuotes">That the Church acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no vain reſemblances,
<note place="margin">Eccleſia inanes ideas, &amp; vanas neſcit ſimulachrorum figuras, ſed veram novit Trinitatis ſubſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam. Lib. de Jacob &amp; Vitâ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ata.</note> nor any vain Figures of Images, but that it acknowledged the true Subſtance of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</q>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor had commanded that the Temples ſhould be in all Cities rendred clear of Images, it was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately apprehended, that he had provided theſe Temples for Chriſt; as <hi>Aelius Lampridius</hi> noteth in the <hi>Life of Alexander Severus.</hi> Which is a convincing Argument, that it was not in uſe with Chriſtians in thoſe days, to have any Images in their Churches.</p>
               <p>This, I ſuppoſe, is enough to demonſtrate, that the ancient
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:63025:29"/>and primitive Church was as great a Stranger to Images, and that it abhorr'd them as much as the Church of <hi>England</hi> does at preſent. Many and large Collections have been made by Proteſtant Writers of the Senſe and Opinions of antient Writers concerning this particular, unto whom I muſt refer the Reader, becauſe the preſent occaſion will not permit me to be prolix or tedious in reciting them. I have examined ſeveral of theſe Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, and find them to be accurate, and this is one princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal motive of my Converſion.</p>
               <p>We ſee by what has been already alledged of what account the uſe of Images was in the ancient and beſt times: Chriſtians then would by no means permit them to be brought into their Churches. Nay, ſome of them would not ſo much as admit the Art it ſelf of making them; ſo jealous were they of the danger, and careful to prevent the deceit, whereby the ſimple might any way be drawn on to adore them.</p>
               <p>Now the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does own that it is very abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to worſhip an Image abſolutely, that is, to make it the principal or ſole object of Adoration. But their evaſion here in is, that a relative Worſhip is not forbidden, nor falleth under the compaſs of Idolatry; that is to ſay, to worſhip an Image in regard of him whoſe Image it is, and by reaſon of the relation it has to him, it is not againſt the Commandment. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that the Worſhip of it after that manner doth not excuſe the Worſhippers from Idolatry, ſince the Commandment is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in general expreſſions, and has no limitation or reſtriction; but it forbids, without exception, all bowing down to them, and worſhipping of them, of what kind ſoever the Worſhip be.</p>
               <p>Had a relative Worſhip of Images been accounted lawful in the primitive ages, certainly the holy Fathers and Councils would not have omitted to acquaint us therewith. But we find the quite contrary: for when the Gentiles demanded of the ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, why they had no known Images, they did not ſay, we have Images to be relatively worſhipped. But <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> returned them this for anſwer;
<note place="margin">Quod enim ſimulachrum Deo fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam, cùm ipſe Homo, ſi recte exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes, ſit Dei ſimulachrum. Mi nut, in Octav.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">What Image ſhall I make of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63025:29"/>God, when Man himſelf, if you rightly judge, is Gods Image?</q>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> diſcourſing about the Duties that ariſe from the firſt Table of the Decalogue, has this following paſſage; <q rend="margQuotes">It is forbidden that any ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of God ſhould be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in things contrived by humane invention;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prohibetur coli aliqua in figmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis hominem Dei ſimilitudo, non quia non habet Imaginem Deus, ſed quia nulla ejus Image coli de b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t niſi illa, quae hoc eſt quod ipſe. Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 119. <hi>ad Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</hi>
                     </note> not but that God has an Image, but becauſe no Image of him ought to be worſhipped, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that one <hi>(meaning Chriſt)</hi> which is the ſame thing with himſelf.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here we ſee St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s Opinion concerning the Senſe of the ſecond Commandment; he judges that worſhiping any ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of God by an invented Figure is herein prohibited, and conſequently relative Worſhip; according to his Judgment, is a tranſgreſſion of a divine Precept.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> agrees moſt exactly with him; He tells us, that <q rend="margQuotes">God would not have himſelf worſhiped in Stones.</q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non vult ſe Deus coli in Lapidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Ambr. Ep.</hi> 31. <hi>ad Valentin.</hi>
                  </note> That is, in Images made of Stone, and I ſuppoſe the caſe will be much the ſame if the Image be made of any other materials.</p>
               <p>By theſe examples we ſee how far the ancient Writers of the Church differ'd in their Opinion concerning Image worſhip from the preſent Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The ancient Writers agree exactly with the Proteſtants, and were altogether of the ſame Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them, although the word or term of Proteſtant was not then known, but is of later times invented to ſignifie them that proteſt againſt the Errors of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall add a few words more concerning the original of this wicked practice. I find by St. <hi>Irenaeus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. <hi>contra He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeſ.</hi> and alſo by others, that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> and his Diſciples wore the firſt that brought Images into the Chriſtian Religion. If the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63025:30"/>Rominiſts will acknowledge theſe for their Patrons, themſelves can tell how much it will redound to their Glory. It is true that this cuſtom of Image worſhip was very ancient, but very hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal alſo, and abominable. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> and his Sectaries were introducers thereof (as I ſaid before,) who had Images, ſome pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Colours, others fram'd of Gold, and of other matter, which they ſaid, were Repreſentations of Chriſt made under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> when Chriſt was here converſant among men. Whence it came to paſs, that <hi>Corpoorates</hi> and his diſciple <hi>Marcellina</hi> (who brought this idolatrous practice to <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of Pope <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicetus)</hi> having privily made Images of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> of <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> did cenſe and worſhip them, as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned does relate, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>contra Heraeſ. cap.</hi> 24. But againſt this wicked practice the ancient Chriſtians did zealouſly and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly declare. Here is the eldeſt inſtance of Image-worſhip in any perſon that ever pretended to be any thing of a Chriſtian; and we may ſee how ſeverely it is cenſur'd, and mark'd with the infamous brand of Hereſie; ſuch then was the firſt riſe of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges among Chriſtians: but there was another cauſe, that much contributed to the advancement of their Worſhip, and that was this; Many ſimple Chriſtians nowly converted from Paganiſm could not unlearn the cuſtoms of it, as it is obſerved by <hi>Euſebius</hi> concerning the image of Chriſt erected by the Woman that was cur'd of the Bloody Iſſue, <hi>Euſeb l 7. Hiſt. Eccleſiaſt. c.</hi> 18. <hi>It is no marvel</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that thoſe of the Heathen, who of old were cured by our Saviour, ſhould do ſuch things, ſince we have ſeen the Images of the Apoſtles St.</hi> Paul <hi>and St.</hi> Peter, <hi>yea and of Chriſt himſelf kept painted with colours in Tables. For they</hi> (that is, converted Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles) <hi>of old were wont by a Heatheniſh cuſtom thus to honour them whom they accounted to be their Benefactors or Preſervers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But by whomſoever they were firſt brought in, certain it is they proved a pernicious allurement to the ſimple people, who ſoon went a whoring after them, contrary to the Command of God, and the Doctrine of the ancient Fathers and Defenders of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>This I find to be the true ſtate of the whole affair concerning
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63025:30"/>Image worſhip, and I am heartily ſorry that I underſtood, it not heretofore. But I hope to obtain pardon, becauſe I labour'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great prejudices of my Education and could not imagine that ſuch grave and learned Doctors as have aſſerted the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Antiquity of Image-worſhip, would have led me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo groſs an Error.</p>
               <p>We are told by ſome of theſe Doctors, and particularly by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalate.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That the veneration of Images oven the moſt ancient,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſiam Chriſtianam etiam an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquiſſimam, totam ac univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſummo conſenſu abſque ullâ oppoſitione aut contradictione ſtatuas ac imaginas veneratam eſſe M. Anton de Domin de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio reditûs ſect.</hi> 23.</note> the whole and univerſal Church did embrace as a Doctrine of Faith; and that with unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſent, and without any oppoſition or contradiction it did worſhip Statutes, and Images.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now for conſutation of this ſhameleſs aſſertion, I appeal to the aforegoing Councils and Holy Fathers; certainly I had reaſon to grow diſſatisfied with the Communion of <hi>Rome,</hi> when I ſaw that their great ſticklers endeavoured to defend their Doctrines by ſuch notorious and manifeſt untruth.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Concerning the Adoration of the Croſs.</head>
                  <p>I Think the worſhip of the material Croſs of Chriſt to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like the worſhip of Images, and that is the cauſe why I have rankt it under this general head, which I aſſign for my fifth Motive. But altho the Devotions paid by the Romaniſts to the Croſs do in ſome reſpects reſemble Image worſhip, yet in many regards they are much worſe: For the Romaniſts do avowedly give <hi>Latria</hi> to the Croſs, and although ſome of them do pretend that this is only given to it relatively; yet if one examine their Hymns and Prayers directed to the Wooden Croſs, it will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appear that their excuſes are trivial, and their pretences vain. None doubts but that our Saviours Sufferings (which are
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63025:31"/>often called the Croſs of Chriſt) do abundantly deſerve our greateſt regard, but then to transfer this to the material and literal Croſs is a wonderful thing, and I am aſtoniſht at my ſelf in that for ſo many years I never conſidered it, or weighted this matter, as I ought to have done. But I ſhall proceed to conſider ſome of the pretences, and excuſes which Roman Catholicks make in order to defend the worſhip of the Croſs</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſayes <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Reliquiis Sanctis, that the Croſs ought to be adored by the fame worſhip with Chriſt, becauſe it was touched by Chriſts Sacred Body.</hi> But if this be true then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is to be worſhiped by the ſame worſhip alſo, by reaſon ſhe carried him nine months in her Womb, ſhe nouriſht him <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and his contact with her was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, with the Croſs violent. But the Romaniſts deny ſuch due to her, therefore of neceſſity they ought to deny it to be due to the holy Croſs.</p>
                  <p>If <hi>Latria</hi> (or ſupreme Worſhip) be due to the Croſs for its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact with Chriſt, it ought rather for that reaſon to be attributed unto the Aſs, whereon Chriſt rid with ſolemnity to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and to the ſeveral Beds, whereon He lay, and Ships, wherein he wafted from Region to Region; becauſe his attingency in and with them was voluntary, with the Croſs coactive. Nay they ought upon the ſame ground to adore <hi>Judas</hi> his lips, the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers hands, that apprehended and bound Chriſt, the Scourges, whereby He was whipt, for they were inſtruments of his paſſion as well as the Croſs.</p>
                  <p>If they adore all other Croſſes for their reſemblance of the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Croſs ſo they ought to adore all Mangers, all Launces, all Nails, Thorns, Spittles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for theſe have the ſame reſemblance to our Saviours Manger, and to thoſe Nails, Thorns <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were the inſtruments of his Paſſion.</p>
                  <p>They attribute more Honour unto Chriſts Croſs than to his Reſurrection by theſe words, <q rend="margQuotes">We adore thy Croſs, and comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate thy Reſurrection.</q> 
                     <hi>Crucem tuam adoramus, reſurrectionem tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am recolimus</hi> They aſcribe then (it ſeems) Adoration to the Croſs which is only proper unto the Divine Nature, and to the Croſs
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63025:31"/>likewiſe (that is to the Wood) they attribute the redemption of the world, and the reconcilation of mankind unto God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>vide Bellarmin lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 23. <hi>ſect. Ac primum.</hi> They alſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute forgiveneſs of Sins, and increaſe of Righteouſneſs to the Croſs, they repoſe their hopes and confidence in the dead Wood of the Croſs, and beg remiſſion of Sins from it; as may be ſeen in their Hymns extant in the <hi>Roman Breviary,</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and reviſed by the authority of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and ſet forth by ſeveral Popes, as may be ſeen in ſeveral Editions of it, eſpecially in that Printed at <hi>Paris anno</hi> 1662 whence I draw this that follows.
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O Crux ave ſpes unica!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In hoc Paſchali gaudio</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Auge piis Juſtitiam,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Reiſque dona veniam.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> That is in Engliſh thus;
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hail O Croſs, our only hope!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In this our Paſchal joy,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Increaſe the Righteouſneſs of the pious,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And give pardon to the guilty.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nothing, doubtleſs, can be more prodigious, unleſs it be what follows,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O Crux ſplendidior cunctis aſtris,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mundo celebris, hominibus multum amabilis,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sanctior univerſis,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Quae ſola fuiſſe digna portare talentum mundi,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dulce Lignum, dulces clavos dulcia ferens pondera,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Salva praeſentem catervam</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In tuis hodie laudibus congregatam.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Alleluja, Alleluja.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> That is in Engliſh thus,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O Croſs! more bright than all the Stars.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Famous through the world, very lovely to mankind.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>More holy than all other things,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which waſt alone worthy to carry the Ranſom of the world,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dear Wood, that carrieſt the dear Nails, and the dear Burden.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:63025:32"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Save the preſent Aſſembly, which is to day gathered together for thy Praiſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Alleluja, Alleluja.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Great Complements, upon my word, for a liveleſs piece of Wood! for that they mean the material Croſs, (and not the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Saviour) their words do abundantly declare. We ſee here they repoſe their hope and conſidence in the Wood; they beg increaſe of Grace from it, and aſcribe to it a Power to forgive Sins, which Attribute appertaineth to the Godhead only.</p>
                  <p>The Humanity of Chriſt, ſeparated from his Divinity, is not to be adored with divine Worſhip, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> teacheth, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil.</hi> 38. <hi>de Verbis Domini.</hi> Therefore much leſs his Croſs, or any other repreſentative Image of his.</p>
                  <p>The Holy Ghoſt is preſent in the Sacrament of Baptiſm; yet it is not to be adored with the ſame Worſhip due to the Holy Ghoſt. Therefore that Wood whereon Chriſt ſuffered, and other Blocks, or Stumps of Trees reſembling it, are not to be adored with the ſame veneration due unto Chriſt. Many conſequences that may be inſerr'd from the Worſhip of the Croſs, and of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, are ſo prodigiouſly abſurd, impious, blaſphemous, and ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, that if I endeavoured exactly to enumerate and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them, I ſhould never come unto an end. Therefore I leave them to the upholders of theſe abuſes, whence they are emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and alſo theſe upholders to truſt to their Images, like to like, <hi>for they that make them</hi> (Pſal. 115.8.) <hi>are like unto them, and ſo is every one that truſteth in them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Prayers in an unknown Tongue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Sixth and laſt Motive or Cauſe of my Declenſion from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is its lack of Charity, in robbing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans not only of the ſuperabundant effects of our Lords Supper,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63025:32"/>by diſmembring it, but alſo of that other effectual Remedy, which Chriſt left unto them, as means whereby they might attain unto Salvation, <hi>viz.</hi> the benefit of Publick Service, or Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, by hindring them to make uſe thereof in the vulgar tongue, intended by God and Nature for all peoples edification. This Common Service, Prayers, Liturgy, or Maſs, which in effect are all one, the Conventicle of <hi>Trent</hi> in the 22th <hi>Seſſ.</hi> and 8th <hi>chap.</hi> denies plainly to be expedient to uſe in the vulgar Tongue, or Idiom: So <hi>Stapleton</hi> the Jeſuit, in his Engliſh Book written againſt Biſhop <hi>Jewel, Artic.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 75. ſays inconſiderately, <hi>that Devotion is rather hindred by uſing it in a known Idiom, than promoted. Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> in the ſecond Book <hi>de Verbo Dei, chap.</hi> 15. endeavours to prove, that anciently Common Prayers were univerſally pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the Latin tongue by all Nations, and conſequently now ought to be ſo.</p>
               <p>This ſelf-ended and fabulous Natration of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> (I beg his leave for ſaying it) is far from truth, and as contrary to Chriſts Ordinance, to the Apoſtolick Practice, and the general Cuſtom of the primitive Church, as Fire and Water, black and white, cold and heat are one to another. Which firſt I prove by the Teſtimonies of Scripture. 2. By the undeniable Authorities of the holy Fathers. 3. By the uſual Practice of all other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Nations. 4. I ſhall endeavour to prove that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath borrowed this practice from ſuch Authors, as it is a ſhame for her to imitate.</p>
               <p>The Teſtimonies of Scripture produced to this effect.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What Chriſt commanded, that ought religiouſly to be obſerved in his Church: but Chriſt by the mouth of his Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> commanded Common Prayers to be uſed in the vulgar Idiom un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the hearers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.9. <hi>So likewiſe you, except ye utter by the tongue words eaſy to be underſtood, how ſhall it be known what is ſpoken? for ye ſhall ſpeak unto the air.</hi> v. 14. <hi>For if I pray in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known tongue, my Spirit prayeth, but my underſtanding is unfruitful.</hi> v. 16. <hi>Elſe, when thou ſhalt bleſs with the Spirit, how ſhall he that occupieth the room of the unlearned ſay</hi> Amen, <hi>at they giving of thanks, ſeeing he underſtandeth not what thou ſayeſt?</hi> And v. 19. <hi>Yea
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63025:33"/>I had rather ſpeak five words with my underſtanding in the Church, that by my voice I might teach others alſo, then ten thouſand words in an unknown tongue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Whatever is done in the Church, that ought to redound to the edification thereof. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 <hi>v.</hi> 26. <hi>How is it then, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? when ye come together, every one of you hath a Pſalm, hath a Doctrine, hath a Tongue, hath Revelation, hath an Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: let all things be done unto edifying.</hi> But an unknown tongue edifies none. <hi>Ibid. v.</hi> 6. <hi>Now, Brethren, if I come to you ſpeaking with tongues, what ſhall I profit you, except I ſhall ſpeak to you ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by revelation, or knowledge, or by propheſying, or Doctrine?</hi> v. 9. as above cited.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the Miniſter prayeth in an unknown tongue, he is a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian to the people, and alſo the people to him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Therefore if I know not the meaning of the voice, I ſhall be unto him, that ſpeaketh a Barbarian, and he that ſpeaketh a Barbarian unto me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. All things ought to be done in the Church with decency, and due order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 40. <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi> But the uſe of Prayers in an unknown tongue is, directly againſt this Rule: becauſe when the Miniſter ſo prayeth, the hearers underſtand not what he ſays, nor conſequently pray, nor ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to any effect; nay, the Miniſter only, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth the Divine Service, prayeth; and ſo the Prayers, which ought to be publick, by this means are become private, which is as oppoſite to the Decency, and right Order of the Church, as Whoremongering to the ſeventh Commandment.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As the Prophets, Chriſt, the Apoſtles, and their true Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors have ſolemnly miniſtred the Rites and publick Office of the Church, even ſo now and perpetually they ought (as far as is poſſible) in the ſame form, manner and method, without alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to be miniſtred. But they miniſtred them in the vulgar Language, according to the capacity of their Hearers, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> abundantly witneſſeth in the aforegoing 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. And beſides many of the Papiſts themſelves own, that Prayers underſtood are far better, and more available; as <hi>Lyranus</hi> on the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> 14. and Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi> in <hi>Comment.</hi> on the ſame
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63025:33"/>chap. Therefore the practice of praying in a known tongue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better, and more effectual for edifying the people ought ſtill to be retained in the Church; whereas ſhe is always to edi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie, and not deſtroy.</p>
               <p>Though the whole ſtream of all the holy Fathers cannot more convincingly prove the certainty of this truth, than St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath done already; yet for the further ſatisfaction of the Reader. I will produce a few Teſtimonies to the ſame purpoſe, ſo preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as not to be avoided. <hi>Baſil the Great in Epiſt.</hi> 63 has theſe following words; <q rend="margQuotes">By the dawning of the day <hi>(ſays he)</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Faithful alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with one voice,
<note place="margin">Illuceſcente jam die pariter un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ore, ac corde omnes fideles, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſionis Pſalmum Deo offerunt, ac ſuis, quiſque verbis reſipiſcentiam. profitetur — Quae conſuetudines. omnibus Dei Eccleſis conſentien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſunt.</note> and one mind, offereth a Pſalm of Thankſgiving unto the Lord, and every one in his own proper ſpeech acknowledgeth his amendment of life— Which practices are conſented unto in all the Churches of God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>How could this cuſtom of uſing Common Prayers with one voice, or language, in <hi>Baſil the Great</hi>'s time, in all Chriſtian. Churches, be plauſible amongſt the faithful, if their Liturgies (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> feigns) had been cuſtomarily uſed in Latin? For it cannot be properly ſaid, that they offered <hi>unâ voce.</hi> Thankſgiving unto the Lord, if they practiſed diverſity of Languages.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirms the ſame, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>in Gen. c.</hi> 8. in theſe words, <q rend="margQuotes">None can be edified by hearing that which he underſtands not.</q>
                  <note place="margin">Nemo (inquit) aedificatur audien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quod non intelligit.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 99. he ſays again, <q rend="margQuotes">Bleſſed be they, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the magnificient Praiſe of the Lord:
<note place="margin">Beatus populus, qui intelligit ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilationem: curramus ad hanc Beatitudinem: intelligamus ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilationem: non eam ſine intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectu ſundamus.</note> let us haſten to this Bleſſedneſs: let us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it: let us not pour it out, unleſs we underſtand it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Hence follows, that few in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can attain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this bleſſedneſs of underſtanding the Lords Praiſe; becauſe it
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:63025:34"/>cannot be compaſſed without perfect knowledge of the Latine tongue, which cannot be acquired without a tedious progreſs in the ſtudy of it; which progreſs is morally impoſſble for the Commonalty, who make up the greateſt number in that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: Yet they are uncharitably, and that contrary to <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines</hi> Admonition, excluded from this Bleſſedneſs, by a new Commandment and Article of Faith, lately ſabricated in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle of <hi>Trent,</hi> to their utter deſtruction. For what profit can they receive that hear a ſound, and are ſtrangers to the meaning of it? it were as good that they were abſent as preſent: and therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> calls this doting kind of ſerving God <hi>Sacrificium ſtultorum,</hi> a Sacrifice of Fools; and ſo really it is: For they that hear it are no further benefited thereby, than they have capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to apprehend it; as <hi>Azorius</hi> learnedly affirms in theſe words, <q rend="margQuotes">Devotion ſprings from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding;
<note place="margin">Affectus conſequitur intellectum; ubi autem earum rerum, quae pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur, aut dicuntur, nullus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur intellectus, ibi exiguus aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git affectus, &amp; conſequenter valdè exiguus fructus.</note> when there is no underſtanding of things that are ſought, or ſaid, there is but little Devotion, and conſequently very little bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit reapt by the hearer.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed according to this grave Doctors opinion, it were as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to them that are not Latiniſts, to have a ſpeechleſs Prieſt ſo ſay Maſs mentally, as one that hath the freedom of ſpeaking to ſay it loudly; for he that cannot ſpeak and hath no ſpeech, and he that hath none to be underſtood is all alike unto the ignorant, in regard of profiting them; which is a thing rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well confirmed by St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in the 4th <hi>Book</hi> of his <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Doctrine,</hi> the 10th <hi>chap.</hi> exciting the people with a great deal of vehemency to refrain from the perverſe cuſtom of praying in an unknown Language, which in no way (ſays he, tends to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. <q rend="margQuotes">There is no cauſe (ſays he) why a man ſhould ſpeak at all, if they for whoſe ſake he ſpeaks underſtand him not.</q> 
                  <hi>Quid prodeſt locutionum integritas, quam non ſequitur intellectus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientis? Cum loquendi nulla cauſa, ſi quod loquimur non intelligunt, propter quos ut intelligant loquimur.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:63025:34"/>
               <p>For God hears the Prieſts thoughts when he ſpeaks not, as well as when he ſpeaks; he hears the Prayers of the Heart, and ſees the Word of the Mind, and a ſpeechleſs Prieſt can do all the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and make the Signs, and he that ſpeaks aloud to them that underſtand him not does no more.</p>
               <p>So the Author of the <hi>Expoſition upon the firſt Epiſtle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> by ſome thought to be St. <hi>Ambroſe, chap.</hi> 14. ſays, <q rend="margQuotes">If ye be convened to edifie the Church,
<note place="margin">Si ad Eccleſiam aedificandam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venitis, ea dici debent, quae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligunt auditores.</note> things ought to be ſpoken, which the hearers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Which Doctrine is plainly ſeconded by <hi>Caſſiodore</hi> upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. in theſe words, <q rend="margQuotes">We ought not only (ſays he) to ſing,
<note place="margin">Non ſolum (inquit) cantantes, ſed intelligentes pſallere debemus; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo enim quidquam facit ſapienter quod non intelligit.</note> but alſo to know and underſtand the ſenſe &amp; mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our ſinging; for none can do any thing rationally, except he knoweth the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And likewiſe by <hi>Jacobus Faber Stapul.</hi> in his <hi>Comment. on</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. who affirms (rebuking the people for their Lewdneſs touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>this particular.) <q rend="margQuotes">That a great part of the world, now a days prayeth,
<note place="margin">Maxima pars hominum cum nunc orat, neſcio ſi Spiritu ſcio tamen quod non mente orat: nam linguâ orat quam non intelligit.</note> but whether their Prayers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the Spirit of God I know not, but I know they pray not from the heart, nor to any effect: becauſe they pray in an unknown tongue.</q>
               </p>
               <p>If the aforegoing incontroulable Authorities of theſe holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be not ſufficient to confute <hi>Bellarmines</hi> groundleſs Surmiſe, and imaginary Comment, by ſaying, <hi>that in the former ages of the primitive Church Common Prayers were generally practiſed in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63025:35"/>Latin amongst the Faithful, and Profeſſors of Chriſtianity;</hi> for his and his Sticklers Diſgrace and Shame, I add <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Lyra ibid.</hi> and <hi>Caſſander Liturg. cap.</hi> 28. who, ſiding with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> do frequently tell us, that Divine Service or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayers in an unknown Tongue do not edifie, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently were forbidden; as I have ſhewn evidently already? To this effect I might produce the torrent of the holy Fathers, who flouriſhed in the ſucceeding ages of the Church, but that I am willing to ſhun prolixity. And ſo I go on to the proof of the third part of my Aſſertion, which is, That the Practical Cuſtom of all Chriſtian Nations anciently was, to pray in their own native Languages, and it is to this very day.</p>
               <p>Here <hi>Origen</hi> in his 8th <hi>Book againſt Celſus</hi> may come in as an impartial Witneſs, teſtifying, that the <hi>Grecians</hi> in their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers uſe <hi>Greek,</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Language; and ſo eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nation according to his Idiom prayeth to God, and praiſeth him as they were able.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Lyra</hi> ſeconds him thus, on 1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 14. affirming, that in the primitive Church Bleſſings, our Lords Prayer, and all other things were done in the vulgar tongue: nay, not only Common Prayers, but the whole Bible was anciently by many Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made fit for the peoples uſe; as St. <hi>Hierom. Epiſt. ad Sophr.</hi> affirms, that himſelf tranſlated the Bible into the <hi>Dalmatian</hi> tongue. And <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lphilas Sozom lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Hiſt. c.</hi> 37. a Biſhop among the <hi>Goths</hi> tranſlated it into the <hi>Gotick</hi> tongue. And that it was tranſlated into all other Languages, we are told by St. <hi>Chryſoſt. Homil.</hi> 1. <hi>in</hi> 8. <hi>S. Joannis.</hi> By <hi>S. Auguſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>de Doctrinâ Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianâ.</hi> And <hi>Theodoret Serm.</hi> 5. <hi>de Graecar. Affect. Curat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides all theſe authentick Teſtimonies of the aforementioned renowned Doctors, who indifferently acquaint all Chriſtians, that in the primitive Church the Prieſt and the People joined together in their Prayers, and underſtood each other, and prayed in their mother-tongue; I will produce for a further and more palpable conviction of this Foppery, the words of the Civil and Canon Law. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the Emperour made a Law in theſe words; <hi>Our Will
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63025:35"/>and Command is, that all the Biſhops and Prieſts do celebrate the Sacrament of Oblation, and the Prayers thereunto added in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Baptiſm with a loud and clear voice, which may be underſtood by the faithful, that thereby the minds of the Hearers may be raiſed up with greater Devotion, to ſet forth the Praiſe of the Lord God; for ſo the Apoſtle teacheth,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Innocent</hi> III. is moſt expreſs herein, in the great General Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> (as themſelves eſteem,) held <hi>anno</hi> 1215. <hi>Can.</hi> 9. where he hath theſe words; <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in many places within the ſame City and Dioceſs the people of divers Tongues are mixt together, having under one and the ſame Faith divers Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Rites, We ſtrictly charge and command, that the Biſhops of ſuch Cities and Dioceſſes provide men fit, who may celebrate the Divine Office according to the diverſity of their Languages,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If you will inquire, why are they not as ſtedfaſt followers of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> in this point, as in that of Tranſubſtantiation? I can give you no other reaſon, but that (I am afraid) they will be called Libertines by their ill-wiſhers, for making uſe of the Laws of God and Man (as they pleaſe) to the advancement of their Self-ended Errors; and for impudently rejecting what is contrary thereunto. Now if the uſual Cuſtom of the Prophets, Chriſts Inſtitution, and exemplary manner of preaching, and teaching to ſay Prayers in an underſtood Language; if the Words of the Apoſtle, the Practice of the primitive Church, the Sayings of the holy Fathers, and Conceſſions of impartial men of their own Communion, if the Conſent of all other Chriſtian Nations, and the Piety of our Forefathers, if right Reaſon and the nature of publick Service it ſelf, if the Needs of the Ignorant, and Condition of the holy Prayers, if the Laws of Princes, and the Laws of the Church, which require all our Prayers to be ſaid according to the Underſtanding of our Auditors; if all theſe cannot prevail with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to do ſo much good to the poor ignorant peoples Souls, as to conſent they ſhould underſtand what in particular they ask of God; aſſuredly, there is great pertinacy of Opinion, and very little Charity to thoſe procious Souls for whom Chriſt ſuffer'd, and for whom they muſt give a ſtrict account.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:63025:36"/>
               <p>And the Papiſts themſelves own, that at this very inſtant of time the <hi>Egyptians, Moſcovians, Sclavonians, Armenians, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopians, Moravians, Bohemians, Hungarians,</hi> the <hi>Jacobites, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſines,</hi> and all other Chriſtian Nations have, in and throughout the whole Univerſe, their Liturgies in their own native Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages. And <hi>Eckius</hi> affirms, that the ſame practice, and no other, is obſerved in the <hi>Indies</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> or any other part of the world amongſt Chriſtians. And that being ſo, it is ſtrange that the Proteſtants ſhould not have the ſame priviledge, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any peremptory Cenſure from the See of <hi>Rome</hi> of being Hereticks, and damned, for doing nothing elſe but what other Chriſtians do.</p>
               <p>As to the proof of the fourth part of this Aſſertion; This prophane cuſtom of Prayers in an unknown Language, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo cloſely ſticks unto, is derived,</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the <hi>Oſſeni</hi> Hereticks, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> affirms, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the <hi>Heracleonites,</hi> of whom St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives an account; ſaying, <hi>That they taught to pray with obſcure words, ſuppoſing that words in a barbarous and unknown tongue might be more powerful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. (If we may give credit to famous Hiſtorians, both ancient and modern,) From the <hi>Jews,</hi> who in their Synagogues, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly formerly, but at this very day, read <hi>Hebrew,</hi> which the people rarely underſtand. And beſides, from the <hi>Turks,</hi> who in their Moſques read <hi>Arabick,</hi> of which the people know nothing.</p>
               <p>The very conſideration of theſe leading Patterns, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does ſo pertinatiouſly imitate herein, have been ſo prevailing with me, as to forſake her Communion, and to embrace that of the Reformed Church, wherein ſurer Guides unto Eternity can be demonſtrated.</p>
               <p>And now having given an account of the Motives of my Change, I have one only Requeſt to make to the candid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; that they would not treat a new Convert as the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did St. <hi>Paul</hi> on his firſt Change, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.26. by being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of me, and not believing me to be a ſincere Proſelyte: for
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63025:36"/>as I never perſecuted any of them in my life, but rather did them all good offices that lay in my power: ſo I hope it will be ſome motive to them to believe my Converſion real, when it is done at a time when they themſelves are not without fears and apprehenſions of Diſadvantage.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe that I (the Writer of the foregoing Book) am in ſome degree a ſtranger to the Engliſh Tongue, I deſire the Reader ingeniouſly to pardon my unskilfulneſs in it, and not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted if he meet with ſome improprieties in the Language; for although by the advice and direction of my Friends many impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per expreſſions were corrected; yet I ſuppoſe that ſome Errors of that nature do ſtill remain.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 22. read <hi>Armenians,</hi> p. 4. in the margin r. <hi>Andradius lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Orthodoxarum Explicationum Reſp. ad Axiom.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp; alii apud Caſalium lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>prim. part. de qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dripert. juſtit.</hi> p. 6. l. 20. r. <hi>taken,</hi> p. 7. l. 25. and afterwards r. <hi>Cataphas,</hi> ib. l. 30. r. <hi>de Conciliorum Authoritate,</hi> p. 8. l. 4. r. <hi>Nation,</hi> ib. in the Latin citation r. <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> p. 15. l. 18. r. <hi>Faith and Duties,</hi> ib. l. 28. r. <hi>nine parts in ten,</hi> p. 16. l. 33. r. <hi>Romiſh Religion,</hi> p. 17. l. 1. r. <hi>to the rights,</hi> ib. l. 2. r. <hi>liberties,</hi> p. 30. l. 5. r. <hi>yet it ceaſes not,</hi> ib. l. 18. r. <hi>for itu,</hi> p. 31. l. 28. r. <hi>he does,</hi> p. 33 in the latin citation of <hi>Lindanus,</hi> r. <hi>id eſt anno Domini,</hi> p 35. in the latin cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Card. <hi>Bona</hi> r. <hi>ſub ſpecie,</hi> ib. r. <hi>communicarunt,</hi> p. 41. l. 8. r. <hi>neceſſity,</hi> p. 42. l. 13. of the latin citation r. <hi>ſacrilega,</hi> p. 43. l. 31. r. <hi>impartial,</hi> ib. l. ult. r. <hi>corporis,</hi> p. 44. l. 11. r. <hi>parting of one,</hi> p. 45. l. 25. r. <hi>reconcilable,</hi> ib. l. 32. r. <hi>Lindanus, who agreeing,</hi> p. 47. l. 7. r. <hi>erroneous,</hi> p. 51. l. 14. r. <hi>therefore,</hi> p. 54. l. 13. r. <hi>Haereſ.</hi> p. 57. l. 3. r. <hi>Bell. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 23. <hi>de Reliquiis ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:63025:37"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for and Sold by</hi> William Norman <hi>and</hi> Eliphal Dobſon.</head>
            <list>
               <item>BIbles and Common Prayers in all volumes.</item>
               <item>Book of Homilies.</item>
               <item>Boltons Statutes.</item>
               <item>Boltons Juſtice of Peace.</item>
               <item>Book of Rates.</item>
               <item>Plurality of Worlds.</item>
               <item>Prayers and Meditations.</item>
               <item>Gawens Logicks.</item>
               <item>Mortons Devotions.</item>
               <item>Dr. Lakes Officium Euchariſticum.</item>
               <item>Dr. Burnets Life of the Earl of Rocheſter.</item>
               <item>Tillotſon againſt Tranſubſtantiation.</item>
               <item>Biſhop of Corks Sermons.</item>
               <item>Silvius de Febribus.</item>
               <item>Mullineux's Sciothericum Teleſcopicum.</item>
               <item>Diſcourſe againſt Purgatory.</item>
               <item>Diſcourſe againſt Auricular Confeſſion.</item>
               <item>The Intereſt of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
